<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Religion and loyalty maintained against all modern opposers in a treatise on the 29th of May 1681, being Trinity-Sunday and anniversary day of His Majesties happy birth and King and kingdoms restauration / by Henry Anderson.</title>
            <author>Anderson, Henry.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 204 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25358</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3092</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27731</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10124063</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10124063</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44571</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25358)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44571)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1374:64)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Religion and loyalty maintained against all modern opposers in a treatise on the 29th of May 1681, being Trinity-Sunday and anniversary day of His Majesties happy birth and King and kingdoms restauration / by Henry Anderson.</title>
                  <author>Anderson, Henry.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 128 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.M. for Will. Abington and Will. Clark,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44571:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>RELIGION AND LOYALTY MAINTAINED Againſt all Modern Oppoſers; IN A TREATISE ON The 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> 1681. being <hi>Trinity-Sunday,</hi> and Anniverſary Day of His Majeſties hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Birth, and King and Kingdoms Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p>By <hi>HENRY ANDERSON,</hi> M.A. Vicar of <hi>Kingſumborne</hi> in <hi>Hampſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>Fear God: Honour the King, <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Pet. 2.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. M.</hi> for <hi>Will. Abington</hi> near the <hi>Wonder</hi>-Tavern in <hi>Ludgate</hi>-ſtreet; and <hi>Will. Clark</hi> Book-ſeller in <hi>Wincheſter.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:44571:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44571:2"/>
            <head>TO THE High and Mighty MONARCH <hi>CHARLES</hi> II. By the Grace of God King of Great <hi>Britain, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the Faith.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Dread Soveraign,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AMongst the multitude of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices which daily offer themſelves to your Sacred Majeſty, of the richer ſort, if this mean Oblation of a Turtle find your Royal Aſpect, ſpeaks only the Grandeur and Heroick Greatneſs of <hi>England</hi>'s Monarch, who darts the diffuſive beams of your Goodneſs (throughout your Realms) on your Liege People by your auspicious and moſt gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Government, being cheriſh'd by the
<pb facs="tcp:44571:3"/> gracious Rays of Soveraign Power, as the obſcure parts of the Earth are by the radiations of the Sun. Theſe happy In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences (like the Dew of <hi>Hermon</hi>) deſcend upon all that are not guilty of Diſloyalty, and trample not on Regal Power in abſtracting their Allegiance; for ſuch are no longer Subjects, but Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, that despiſe Dominions, and ſpeak evil of Dignities, contemning the bright and ſplendid Crown of Soveraignty. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and Divine is Royal Majeſty, as it is a reflection of that above, and it is the Glory thereof to protect things Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred; therefore it looks ſo high, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixes ſo mighty a Name, which can give a ſufficient value to things in themſelves both mean and worthleſs, however im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, your favour is able to ſupply, and give it life, if the production be not unworthy you Royal Patronage: yet it is not improper to lay it at the feet of Majeſty, becauſe the Holy Trinity, that Theological Myſtery, is the Article
<pb facs="tcp:44571:3"/> of our Creed, and it can't take a more rever'd Sanctuary for its ſafety than the Defender of the Faith, whoſe prudent and Princely Conduct crowns all our Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licities with a calm Tranquillity in Church and State; therefore let us ſerve the Lord our God and <hi>Charles</hi> our King, whom he hath raiſed up unto us. Long, long may you flouriſh with a Crown of Glory on your head, and a Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter of Triumph in your hand, bathing your feet in the blood of your Enemies, and live to be, as you are, the delight and glory of your People, and we truſt under your ſhadow, being not only to <hi>Moſes</hi> a Protection, but to all the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> that wait at the Altar; and the great Argoſie, the Ship Royal of the Church, would have daſh'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the rocks, and been ſwallowed up by the quick Sands, or by the malignity of croſs and contrary Winds (of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Religious Crew who delight in Blood and Treaſon) unleſs your Sacred
<pb facs="tcp:44571:4"/> Majeſty, who as a Guardian Angel, that ſits at the Stern, by ſome propitious gales from Heaven, had guided and conducted her to the fair Havens of Peace. As Protection, ſo it humbly craves Acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptance, becauſe goodneſs is the honour of Greatneſs, and that Perſian Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch was not more famous for accepting a little water from the hand of a loving Subject, than your Sacred Majeſty is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown'd through <hi>Britain</hi>'s Orb for your gracious Clemency to all, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to the Offerings of the Sons of <hi>Aaron,</hi> though this Piece bluſhes at the confidence of its Dedication, as not worthy the approach of Royal Preſence, or Majeſty's judicious Eye, being like the ſtraw and brick of <hi>Egypt,</hi> very inconſiderable in regard of the poliſhing, carving and Cedar-work of the Temple, performed by a <hi>Bezaleel</hi> and <hi>Aholiab,</hi> that can curiouſly work in Gold; yet I contribute my Mite, and caſt my little into the Treaſury, but with ſuch humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb facs="tcp:44571:4"/> preſented as ſpeaks Loyalty, and not preſumption, ſhewing the World in all expreſſions of a grateful mind, and ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the greateſt affection, where Duty binds me to pay the Fealty and Homage of my Obedience: Celebrating the Memory of this Day<note n="*" place="margin">May 29.</note> with ebulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Joy and Satisfaction, as it car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries the propitious Star of Royal Birth, with a Conſtellation of Bleſſings to the Kingdom in a happy and peaceable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration. Almighty Goodneſs ſetled us on our old Baſis, and by a Miracle of Providence reſtored to us our Prince, Religion and Government, for which Mercy we magnifie the Glorious and Eternal Trinity, humbly beſeeching the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to your Regal Majeſty a long and proſperous Reign over us, with an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of Health and Wealth, Triumphs and Conqueſts here; and when you ſhall put off the Glories of a Temporal Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, and lay down your mortal Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem,
<pb facs="tcp:44571:5"/> you may exchange it for an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Crown eternal in the Heavens, being incircled with the Rays of Glory and Happineſs in a Life that never pays Tribute to Death. So prays</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Majeſty's moſt humble, obedient and Loyal Subject,</hi> Henry Anderſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44571:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE HOLY TRINITY ASSERTED, AND MONARCHY MAINTAINED Againſt all diſloyal Opponents, in a Treatiſe on the 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> 1681. being <hi>Trinity-Sunday,</hi> and Anniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Day of His Majeſties happy Birth, and King and Kingdoms Reſtauration.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 73. verſ. 25.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Whom have I in Heaven but thee? And there is none upon Earth that I deſire beſides thee.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1-71" type="pages">
               <p>COntentment is the univerſal Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to which all the thoughts, actions, and contrivances of Men tend; the point to which they are all
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:44571:6"/> directed, is ſatisfaction. This is the great ſpring to all the various motions of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind: and however diſtant and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry their ways and courſes, their inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and conſtitutions are; yet here they all meet and concenter in this one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling object. Contentment and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction is that which the Learned ſeeks to obtain, in his induſtrious queſt after Knowledge. This Jewel the Merchant ſeeks in his dangerous Voyages, the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious in his paſſionate purſuit of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, the covetous in his unwearied heaping up of Treaſure, the wanton in his pleaſing Charms of Beauty, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour in his earneſt deſires of Victory, and the Politician in his deep Deſigns. But alas! the miſery of Man is, That he would find that in the variety of the Creatures, which is no where to be found but in the unity of the Creator, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt. For abſolute content dwells not here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. It is not in Granaries fill'd with plenty, in ambitious <hi>Haman</hi>'s ſtate and grandeur, in <hi>Samſon</hi>'s lovely <hi>Dalilah</hi>'s, in <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s Rule over the World; it muſt ariſe from no other ſpring but God the Holy Trinity alone, who is the only Principal of Being, and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of true content. And King <hi>David</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:44571:6"/> draws a right line to the immoveable Center, and directs the Soul to the true Zenith of happineſs, God himſelf, <hi>Whom have I Heaven but thee?</hi> God alone is the pureſt Truth, the chiefeſt Good, and final End of intelligent Beings, which ſpeaks the excellency of Chriſtianity, in reference to the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or ſublimity of its object, which is not the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Univerſe, or boundary of the World; but God the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, from whence all goodneſs flows, the reſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and tranquillity of all Creatures. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in his Metaphyſicks ſaith, That God is <hi>vivens, aeternus &amp; optimus,</hi> a living, eternal and tranſcendent Good. <hi>Plato</hi> in his Book <hi>de Legibus</hi> ſaith, That God is <hi>bonus, &amp; cauſa bonorum omnium,</hi> good, and the cauſe of all good things. And <hi>Cicero</hi> contemplating God in the happy fruition of himſelf, ſaith, <hi>Ea eſt Dei vita quâ nihil beatius, nihil omnino bonis omnibus affluentius cogitari poteſt; nihil enim agit, nullis occupationibus eſt implicatus, nulla opera molitur, ſuâ poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ &amp; virtute gaudet, habet exploratum fore ſe ſemper tum maximis tum in aeternis voluptatibus: i. e.</hi> Such is the life of God, than which nothing is more happy, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the world can be thought to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound with more good things; he is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44571:7"/> implicated in no buſieneſs, he undergo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no labour, but enjoyeth his own power and virtue, and knows certainly that he ſhall be always in tranſcendent pleaſures. God is the Haven of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Felicity, where till we arrive in ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Spirits, we are mazed in endleſs wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings, tortur'd on the rack of ſelf-vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<note n="*" place="margin">Cor humanum in deſiderio aeternitatis non fixum, nunquam ſtabile poteſt eſſe, ſed omni vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lubi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itate volubilius, de alio in aliud tranſit, quaerens requiem ubi non eſt. In his autem ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducis &amp; tranſitoriis, in quibus ejus affectus captivi tenentur, veram requiem invenire non valet: quoniam tantae eſt dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis, ut nullum bonum praeter ſummum bonum, ei ſufficere poteſt. <hi>S Auguſt.</hi>
                  </note>, our deſires know no ſhore or bottom. And there is no man but feels his Soul too big for terreſtrial things, too noble to glut it ſelf with baſe corporeal pleaſures, and the Underſtanding too ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime a faculty to ſubject it ſelf to a brutiſh appetite; theſe things are never able to fill its vaſt capacities, but only the glorious Trinity, its Maker, and leaves no room for ſorrow to creep in. For the heart of man is triangular, which the whole circle of the world cannot fill (as Mathematicians ſay) but all the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, will complain of emptineſs for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe. Nothing can fill the heart o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> man but God. Nothing can ſatisfie it but the Divinity it ſelf. There is no thing can give reſt to the Soul, but only him that made it; for the heart of man i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> like the Needle of the Compaſs, it hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:44571:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> a natural trembling to the Pole, even the fruition of bliſs. And then will the Soul be pleaſed, when it lies down in the lap of Eternity, and the Triple An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle of mans heart ſatisfied, being united to God, the fountain of happineſs, where the Angels ſun themſelves for ever: and the Myſtery of the Sacred Trinity ſhall be in full revelation, and that inconcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable joy ſhall be open'd to you, which changes not as the Moon, eclipſed as the Sun, nor ſet as the Stars. Holy <hi>David</hi> having trave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed and courſed the whole world in his thoughts, for a reſting place (like <hi>Noah</hi>'s Dove) finds not amidſt the ſwelling Tides of this world, whereon to ſtay his feet, returns back again to the Ark with this Olive-branch in his mouth, <hi>Non eſt mortale quod opto.</hi> He finds no ſanctuary but in Heaven, no ſafe repoſe but in the Almighty, <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but thee? And there is none upon Earth that I deſire beſides thee.</hi> The Royal Prophet ſeems to be now under the ſtorms of grief and trouble, and placed as it were <hi>inter ſuſpiria &amp; lachrymas,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſighs and tears; yet he anchors his hopes upon Providence, and chearfully looks up to Heaven, fetching comfort from thence with a full aſſurance of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine favor, and in all preſſures or difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44571:8"/> whatſoever takes himſelf to his Harp, and plays this divine Anthem, <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but thee? And there is none upon Earth that I deſire beſides thee.</hi> The words being Muſical, I ſhall follow the Allegory, and in it obſerve theſe Two generals, <hi>viz.</hi> The diſpoſition of parts, and the oppoſition of the notes on both. The diſpoſition of parts are <hi>Aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratum</hi> and <hi>Lene,</hi> high and low.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> High in a rational expoſtulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Whom have I Heaven but thee?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Low in a poſitive determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>And there is none upon Earth I deſire beſides thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the expoſtulation there are theſe notes in a divine <hi>Climax.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Quem in Coelis? Whom have I in Heaven?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Quem praeter te? Whom have I beſides thee?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Quis mihi? Who is for me?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Quem in Coelis? Whom have I in Heaven?</hi> The Holy Trinity is the Ocean of all true felicity, the comfort, the joy and bliſs of Souls. How ſhould we long after thee, and the fruition of that happineſs, which thou haſt laid up for thoſe that fear thee! In that moſt glorious ſtate theſe operations are moſt ſpecially recommended, and ſpoken of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:44571:8"/> by the Scriptures, <hi>viz.</hi> Viſion, Dilection and Fruition. They ſhall be poſſeſſed with ſuch a ſweet trinity of ſight, love and joy, that the Soul will confeſs, being in an ecſtaſie of wonder and amazement, that it could not believe thoſe things which now it ſees with its eyes, in that it can look no way but it beholds un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable glory. And the Soul ſolacing it ſelf with infinite content, cryes out, <hi>Here will I dwell and abide for ever.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 132.14.</note> Now whilſt others lay up treaſures on Earth, in Heaven is my Exchequer. Our Souls will be irregular like the Planets in their Epicycles; and whilſt we are in the Sphere of fleſh, and cloathed with mortality, ſailing in the Sea of this world, there will be winds to create ſtorms: but in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven there is a perpetual calm, no tempeſt in it; the Soul will joy in Gods Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting reſt. And this is the divine ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of <hi>David</hi>'s ſpirit, <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but thee?</hi> It is the glory and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Soul, to be originally from Heaven. How ſuitable, and how natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral is it for the rational Soul which comes down from Heaven to look thither, and tend towards the ſource and fountain of its Being! <hi>Os homini ſublime dedit, coelúm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que tueri juſſit</hi>— How hard a thing is it to keep the flame from pointing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards?
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:44571:9"/> And with what unwearied <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence do the Rivulets ſeek out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the main Ocean? Such an eager purſuit, ſuch ſtrong propenſions (nay far ſtronger) may be juſtly expected in the Soul to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven, ſeeking the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, things above; To ſeek there <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>an habitation not made with hands,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Eternal in the Heavens,</hi> in as much as the <hi>End</hi> is incomparably greater, and the <hi>Agent</hi> more noble and active: for the heavenly Faculty having capacities ſo wide, and mighty Energies, was ſurely not created to ſerve mean or narrow deſigns; it was not given to ſcrape eternally in earth, or heap up gold for private injoyment, to weary our ſelves with ſervile toils, to diſtract the mind with ignoble cares (this was not the Errand for which we are ſent into the World) but to find out happineſs. We muſt not think God beſtow'd im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Souls upon us, that we might fix them on ſenſual objects, when we find that they are capable of ſuch riches and pleaſures as fade not away. We muſt ſuppoſe, that to do ſo, is the principal and ſupreme End of our Creation. And it is an employment congruous to the native excellency of that Divine power implanted in us, for God hath made us
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:44571:9"/> for himſelf, and unquiet is mans heart until it attains him; <hi>it longs for,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 42.2.</note> 
                  <hi>and thirſts after the living God:</hi> here's one of the ſweet ſtrains of <hi>David</hi>'s Harp, <hi>Whom have I in heaven but thee?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Quem praeter te? Whom have I beſides thee?</hi> Say thou, O Lord, unto my Soul, I am thy Salvation, and it is enough to bleſs and raiſe me above the icy hills of worldly joys. For the bleſſed Trinity is a Chriſtians portion, he is truly poſſeſt of nothing but the Deity, <hi>Whom have I beſides thee?</hi> How glorious art thou in Heaven above! and what infinite happineſs is there provided for me in thee! One day in thy Courts, O Lord, is better than a thouſand elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where in the Palaces of ſinful pleaſures, or Tabernacles of wickedneſs. How then may I, or can I take full content or delight in any thing that is here below? For I envy not ſecular glory nor ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous habitations of the ungodly: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all delicious enjoyments in this life without thee, will but make a Paradiſe without a Tree of Life. King <hi>David</hi> weighed them in the balance of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, and did not only find them <hi>TE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>KEL</hi> too light, but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to ſpeak in the Epigrammatiſts Language, meer nothing to ſpiritual <hi>comfort.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 4.6.</note> The
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44571:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> gleanings of Spirituals are better than the vintage of Naturals and Morals, and the leaſt ſpangle of happineſs is above a globe of Temporals<note n="*" place="margin">Da, Domine, ut ſic poſſidea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus temporalia, ut non perdamus aeterna. <hi>S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard.</hi>
                  </note>; for when all the flaſhes of ſenſual pleaſures are quite ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct, when all the flowers of ſecular glory are withered away, when all earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excellencies are buried in darkneſs, when this world and all the faſhion of it are utterly vaniſh'd and gone, the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite ſpaces of Eternity do yet remain; traffick therefore with the Talent of time,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.16. Luke 19.15.</note> for the unſpeakable advantages of Life eternal, becauſe all our enjoyments un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Tropick of Mortality are fleet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and tranſitory. Some are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Lovers of honours, and theſe are as a flux and reflux of the Sea, for the ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious mans joys and heightned delights, in which his Soul is ſteep'd and inebria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, his Muſick and Feaſting, his ample Building, and Train of Attendants, the Purple and fine Linen, and whole Page<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antry<note n="‖" place="margin">Quid hâc va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ &amp; inani gloriâ fallaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius? quòd ſi in hac vita prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenti viciſſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem hanc e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vadit, omnino mors veniens foelicitatem reſecabit. Et quem hodie in foro magna pompa co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitabatur, &amp; qui in carcerem conjiciebat, &amp; ſuper thronum reſidebat, &amp; inflabatur, &amp; homines alios, quaſi um bras deſpiciebat, is ſubitò poſtea jace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit mortuus abſque ſpiritu, foetulentus, petitus innumeris convitiis, &amp; his, quos pridem injuriâ affecit, &amp; quos nullâ affecit injuriâ: condolentibus ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men his, qui ab iſto injuriâ afflicti ſuerunt. Quid hoc miſerabilius fuerit? Item collecta omnia ſaepenumerò inimici &amp; hoſtes inter ſe partiuntur &amp; diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bnunt: peccata autem per quae haec coacervata ſunt ſecum aufert, de quibus diligens &amp; accurata ratio exigetur. <hi>S. Chryſoſtom. Hom. 22. in Gen.</hi>
                  </note> of Greatneſs, hath but a ſad E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho, <hi>Obad.</hi> 4. <hi>Though thou exalt thy ſelf as the Eagle, and ſet thy neſt among the Stars, thence I will bring thee down, ſaith the Lord.</hi> The ambitious man enlargeth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:44571:10"/> his deſires as Hell, ſaith the Prophet,<note place="margin">Hab. 2.5.</note> and is as death, and cannot be ſatisfied. Who can fill the bottomleſs pit? or ſtop the unſatiable jaws of death? neither can the greedy humor of an haughty Spirit, the aſpiring inſolency of a boiſterous <hi>Nimrod</hi> be poſſibly ſtayed or ſtinted, no not with the top and variety of higheſt honours, though he ſhould alone and abſolutely be crown'd with the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty of the whole Earth, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the felicities of the wide World; but though their excellency mount up to the Heavens, ſaith <hi>Job,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 20.6, 7.</note> and his head reach unto the Clouds, yet they ſhall periſh. Others are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Lovers of money; and riches, ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 23.5.</note> make themſelves wings and fly away: there is a gadding vein in money which makes it ever and anon ſhift maſters, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in <hi>Pythagoras</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Pythag. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>; and who would weary himſelf to purſue the wind? they can reap nothing but vanity and emptineſs;<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.10.</note> therefore let us not ſing a <hi>Requiem</hi> to our Souls, of ſafety and peace, and anchor our hearts and hopes on an earthly Paradiſe, but in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah,</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:44571:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> who is everlaſting Riches. Others are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>2 Tim. 3.4.</hi> Incipit homini occurrere talis jucundi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, qualem ſolet habere in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis, in prandiis, in avaritia, in honoribus ſeculi. Extollun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur enim homines, &amp; laetitiâ quâdam inſaniunt: ſed non eſt gaudere impiis, dicit Dominus; eſt enim jucunditas quaedam, quam nec oculus vidit, nec auris audivit, nec in cor hominis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendit. <hi>S. Aug.</hi>
                  </note>, Lovers of pleaſures, but alas! they quickly fade. A Painter who hath made a pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of a face ſmiling, on a ſudden with no more than one daſh of his Pencil can make it ſeem to weep: the confines of joy and ſorrow border on each other. In the twinkling of an eye, in the turning of an hand, ſadneſs may juſtle out mirth; and deep ſighs may be fetched from that breaſt whence loud laughter made its eruption. Pleaſure may die in the ſame moment that gave it its birth, and a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſucceſſion of grief may turn its cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle into a grave. The tears which an enlarged and vehement paſſion of joy had run over with, may in the middle of their courſe find an Arreſt, and be made to miniſter unto grief in the flight of a minute, in the beating of a pulſe; the dilating of the heart, by a Diaſtole of pleaſure, may be turn'd into a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction by a Syſtole of ſorrow: So all worldly glory, wealth, or pleaſures may well have that Inſcription which <hi>Plutarch</hi> tells us was upon the Temple of <hi>Iſis,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:44571:11"/> We knock at every Creatures door, but there's nothing within, no filling en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment for the Soul. The Father<note n="*" place="margin">It is often in <hi>Homer,</hi> that God is the Father of Spirits, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the Father of Angelical Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and of the Souls of men.</note> of Spirits hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired into our immortal Souls an infinite appetite, that no finite excellency, created comfort, or earthly thing can poſſibly fill. Gold, Silver, Riches, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Crowns, Kingdoms are no fit mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or adequate object for ſuch an imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial and heaven-born Spirit to repoſe and feed upon with delectation and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, but it would ſtill be tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a paſſionate diſquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs<note n="‖" place="margin">Non ſatiat animum niſi incorruptibilis gaudii vera &amp; certa aeternitas. <hi>S. Auguſt.</hi>
                  </note>, until it faſten and fix upon an object infinite both in excellency and endleſneſs, wherein is contained the whole latitude of Entity and Goodneſs, the ever bleſſed and only adored Trinity. Which doth convince men, That compleat happineſs in this Life is a meer Speculation, and it is not to be had in the valley of tears, but in the poſſeſſion of ſuperlative Felicities; let us therefore beſiege Heaven with our united forces,<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 11.12. Faith is <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentum ad ſcandendum coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum,</hi> and Prayer is <hi>clavis coeli,</hi> the Key that opens the Cabinet where the Jewel lies, no other Artillery but this can batter the Citadel of the great King, for Heaven it ſelf can't be proof againſt Petitions often darted to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it, but the violen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> will take it by force.</note> Faith and Prayer, and raiſe ſuch batteries againſt Gods gates,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:44571:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> that we may break open thoſe everlaſting doors, and take the Treaſures of Eternity. <hi>Livy</hi> tells us, That the <hi>Gauls,</hi> when they had taſted the Wines of <hi>Italy,</hi> were ſo much taken with the pleaſantneſs and luſciouſneſs of them, that they would not after reſt contented with a bare Commerce and Trade thither, but fixed their reſolutions by Conqueſt to get poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Land that brought it forth. Thus the Antepaſts of Glory do but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the deſires, and erect the appetite of the believing Soul: he is ſo far from being ſatisfied by foretaſtes or comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble intercourſe, which it enjoys in part with the bleſſed Trinity, by the Word, Sacraments, and other holy Ordinances, that they do but augment his thirſt after a plenary fruition out of the during Well-ſprings of Life and Immortality; therefore his reſolves are by a holy vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and conqueſt to get a poſſeſſion in that ſpiritual <hi>Canaan</hi> from whence theſe Grapes are brought as Prelibations, that he may drink of that Wine of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and of thoſe Rivers of pleaſure: <hi>Whom have I beſides thee?</hi> Thou, O God, doſt far ſurpaſs all the contents of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as light doth pitch'd darkneſs, thou art the joy of my heart, and my portion for ever; aim then at delights which tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:44571:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> Souls, raviſh Angels, and force Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphims into ecſtaſies.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Quis mihi? Who is for me?</hi> Who pleads my cauſe in Heaven? not any Saint or Angel, nor yet the Holy Virgin<note n="*" place="margin">The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> gives <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> to Saints in Heaven, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> more Worſhip to the B. Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin: But the Church of <hi>England,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. For the glory of religious Worſhip is not to be given to any Saint or Angel, though never ſo bleſſed and glorious. S. <hi>John</hi> falling at the feet of the holy Angel, with an intent to worſhip him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.8, 9. met with a timely prohibition, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>See thou do it not:</hi> if that Spirit no leſs hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than glorious bright, had not given him to know that he was hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fellow-ſervant; that honour belongs to our Maſter only, and not to me; <hi>worſhip God.</hi> Here let us remember thoſe excellent words of S. <hi>Auſtin, Tutiùs &amp; jucundiùs loquar ad meum Jeſum, quàm ad aliquem ſanctorum Spirituum Dei;</hi> I can ſpeak ſafer and more pleaſantly, or chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, to my Lord Jeſus, than to any of the Saints and Spirits of God. If praying to Saints, or Angels, or the Holy Virgin had been a uſeful piece of Chriſtian devotion, that during above 4000 years that God had a Church in the World, not one example (ſaith the Reverend Dr. <hi>B.</hi> in his <hi>Miſſale Romanum</hi>) is recorded in Scripture, of any Holy man, who ever called upon any created Saint or Angel: And how is it like or poſſible, that the univerſal Church in after times ſhould learn either new ways towards Heaven, or new ways of true help and comfort, which neither Patriarchs, nor Prophets, nor Apoſtles ever taught or knew? As the Pagans took the Idea of their <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Demono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy from the Scriptures account of the true Meſſiah; ſo in like manner the Papiſts received the original Idea of their <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Saint-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip from this Pagan Demonology; as 'tis evident from 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, rarely demonſtrated by <hi>Mede,</hi> in a Treatiſe called, <hi>The Apoſtaſie of the latter Times.</hi>
                  </note>, but thou, O Lord. And do not ſome dote on Images<note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſays in relation to Images, <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium non eſt, quin religio nulla ſit, ubicun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſimulacrum eſt:</hi> Where-ever an Image is (meaning for Worſhip) there is no Religion; for it robs God of honour, who will not have his glory given to another, nor his praiſe to graven Images, promulgated by his own holy Law. The Greek Church ſpeaks emphatically, We do not forbid Pictures, the Art is noble, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>— but their ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and worſhip we deteſt, as forbidden by the Holy Ghoſt in holy Scripture, <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.18, 19. leſt we ſhould ignorantly adore Colours, Art, and the Creature inſtead of our Creator. They worſhip the Creature (ſaith S. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 1.25.) <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, beſides the Creator, ſo it ſhould be read: if we worſhip any Creature beſides God, worſhipping ſo, as the worſhip of him becomes a part of Religion, is a direct Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition; therefore it is good reaſon, that the Watchmen who ſtand upon the Lords Tower, and tell what of the night ſhould decry the darkneſs of Idolatry and Superſtitition, and warn the people, that they may neither be taken into the whirlpools of danger, nor carried down the ſtream of ungodlineſs; but walk in the ways of Scripture and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, contending for that Faith which forbids all worſhip of Images.</note> with the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts, and others on Imaginations with
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:44571:13"/> Factioniſts, who fall into the heat of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, the fire of Schiſm. How few are in the right way of Gods preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? which is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Lord our God is one Lord. Unity is written in the high Court of Bliſs in Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Glory, and ought it not to be in golden Characters or capital Letters here below to be ſeen and read of all men, and be ſet as a Copy for others to write after? Chriſtians ſhould live on Earth as Angels do in Heaven, not diſagreeing among themſelves. Many that would be lookt upon as living ſtones in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual building, go about to demoliſh ſo fair a ſtructure, by bringing into the Temple the noiſe of axes and hammers; and when they may be ſharers in the Communion of Saints, and bear a chief
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:44571:13"/> part in that ſpiritual conſort, put all out of tune by Separation and Diviſion<note n="*" place="margin">Vos ergo qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſacrilegâ ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratione, pacis vinculum diri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puiſtis? <hi>Auguſt. lib. 2. de Bapt. cont. Donat.</hi>
                  </note>. O tell it not in <hi>Gath,</hi> they who are of the Miniſtration, and ſhould be Ring-leaders in Obedience and Conformity, are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come pernicious Nurſeries of Fanatick Rage, Sedition and Rebellion, <hi>Factio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num &amp; diſcordiarum Duces,</hi> as it was ſaid of the Syndicks of <hi>Geneva.</hi> The dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous malady of Faction made S. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> with ſuch zeal and fervor declare againſt it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>— <hi>I ſay and proteſt</hi>
                  <note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chryſ. in Epheſ. Hom. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>to make Schiſm in the Church is no leſs evil than to fall into He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie.</hi> Behold therefore how good and pleaſant a thing it is for Brethren to dwell together in Unity? It calls to mind that rich Perfume and coſtly Ointment, even thoſe precious drops of love, which fell from the head of the firſt Being to the skirts of inferior Entities. The win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of Heaven are open to us in a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Light, teaching us how to demean our ſelves in a ſtate of Conjunction, as Members of the Catholick Church, not to be ſwelled with rage and fury, but big with Charity and univerſal kindneſs to the whole World, heaping thoſe coals of Love, Bleſſing and Prayer on our Enemies heads;<note place="margin">Mat. 5.44.</note> for a Chriſtian is not to hate his Enemy, but at the ſame rate and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:44571:14"/> expence he loves his friend. Would you be revenged? there's no way to compaſs this deſign, but by the contrary methods of compaſſion and affection. If we would juſtifie our wrath, curteſie muſt be the Executioner overcoming evil with good. Chriſtianity takes away all malice and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, revenge and cruelty out of mens minds; it calms the temper, and fills them with kindneſs and good will, even to their very enemies. And it is moſt certain, that living in Religion and Fear of God, in Obedience to the King, in Charities and Duties of Communion with our ſpiritual Paſtors, Guides and Curates of the Soul, in Juſtice and Love with all the World in their ſeveral proportions, we ſhall not fail of a happy End:<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.8.</note> For <hi>Godlineſs hath the promiſe of this life, and of that which is to come;</hi> but without Piety<note n="*" place="margin">Principibus ad ſalutem ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la ſatis vera eſt pietas; abſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> illa verò nihil eſt vel exercitus, vel Imperatoris ſortitudo, vel apparatus reliquus. <hi>Zoz. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Hiſt. lib. 9. cap. 1.</hi>
                  </note> there is no internal comfort to be found in Conſcience, nor external peace to be looked for in the World, nor eternal happineſs to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for in Heaven. There is no man indeed can expect the favour of God on the ſervice of an hiſtorical and verbal<note n="‖" place="margin">Our Religion conſiſts not in words, but deeds, ſaith <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin.</hi>
                  </note> Piety, or without confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of our affections to his Law. Our Conſciences tell
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:44571:14"/> us,<note place="margin">
                     <p>It is not a Theory to talk only, but to be, makes Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, ſaith <hi>Ignatius.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The ſumm of Chriſtian Religion is to imitate him whom thou worſhippeſt, ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ye know theſe things</hi> (ſaith our Saviour to his Diſciples) <hi>happy are ye, if you do them:</hi> here's knowing and doing, like the two Cherubims, turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both their faces to the Mercy-ſeat of Bleſſedneſs.</p>
                  </note> That it is no better than Blaſphemy to praiſe his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, if we are not govern'd by it; or his Goodneſs, if we do not imitate it. It is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs and affront to look obſequiouſly with eyes and hands lift up to God in our Devotions, whom we ſcorn and revile in our lives and actions. It is the ſpecial glory of our Religion, that it conſiſts not in barren Speculations, or empty Formalities, not in fanſying curiouſly, or ſpeaking zealouſly, or looking de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murely; but in really pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing the ſenſible fruits<note n="*" place="margin">Humilitas in converſatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, ſtabilitas in fide, verecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia in verbis, in factis juſtitia, in operibus miſericordia, in moribus diſciplina, injuriam facere non nôſſe, &amp; factam to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerare poſſe, cum fratribus pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem tenere, Deum toto corde di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligere, amare in illo quod Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eſt, timere quod Deus eſt, Chriſto nihil omninò praeponere, quia nec nobis ille quicquam praepoſuit charitati ejus inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabiliter adhaerere— Quando de ejus nomine &amp; honore certamen eſt, exhibere in ſermone conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, quâ confitemur: in quaeſtione fiduciam, quâ congredimur: in morte patientiam, quâ coronamur. Hoc eſt cohaeredem Chriſti velle eſſe; hoc eſt praeceptum Dei facere; hoc eſt voluntatem Patris adimplere. <hi>S. Cyprian de Orat. Domin.</hi>
                  </note> of goodneſs. Religion, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it is truly planted, is certainly the greateſt obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon Conſcience to all Civil Offices and Moral Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which are the great bands of peace and unity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men; for Chriſtianity in the love and practice of it, is a Principle of truth and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:44571:15"/> fidelity, of ſobriety and diſcretion, of humility and condeſcenſion, of pity and forgiveneſs. It teaches us kindneſs and humanity, which are apt to ſubdue the moſt rugged diſpoſitions, and obliges the hearts and affections of mankind to the ſervice of one another, removing the occaſions of paſſion and diſpleaſure, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects irregularities, and mortifies all thoſe luſts which are the cauſe of enmity and diviſion. The Chriſtian Religion (ſaith our worthy Dioceſan in his Tracts<note n="*" place="margin">Biſh. of <hi>Win.</hi> in his Sermon on the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Novemb.</hi> before the King, <hi>pag.</hi> 15.</note>) truly ſo called, is ſo far from being a cauſe of commotion or diſturbance in Kingdoms and States; that where the Chriſtian Religion is truly taught and truly practiſed, it would be impoſſible there ſhould be any diſſenſion or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, any open Rebellion, or privy Conſpiracy in a State<note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <hi>Fulgentius</hi> ſaith, That no kind of Sedition can ſtand with Religion, <hi>cùm pro noſtra fide liberè respondemus, &amp;c.</hi> When we anſwer freely for our profeſſion, we ought not to be taxed with the leaſt ſuſpicion of diſobedience or contumely, ſeeing we are not unmindful of the Regal Dignity, and do know, that we muſt fear God, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the King, according to the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17.</note> or Kingdom: becauſe all the Articles of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith, and all the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of Chriſtian practice, tend unto peace. Charity, Love and Peace are a ſacred Trinity, and the great Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of Chriſts Diſciples, though many in this degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Age are Jews in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian habit, not admitting
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:44571:15"/> Chriſt a Being in their hearts, living in direct contrariety to his Life and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine by Irreligion and Atheiſm, and had they a power anſwerable to their wills, would un-deifie their Creator. And if his Mercy were not as infinite as his Majeſty, his provoked Soveraignty might in a moment reduce them into their firſt Nothing: Do they not call Chriſt their King by the ſame kind of Irony by which the Jews called him theirs, when platting a Crown upon his head, and putting upon him a Purple Robe, they bow their knees, and cry, <hi>Hail, King of the Jews?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 19.2, 3.</note> They cut down branches and ſpread them in the way, ſinging, <hi>Hoſanna to the Son of David,</hi> when they part his garments, and for his veſture caſt Lots. And whatever dreſs they put on, diſplay them to be a ſpurious brood within the pale, but no true Sons of the Church; were they ſo, their looks would not ſpeak ſmiles, whilſt ſtorms did ſurge in their breaſts, who about the froth of their own brains dare rent the peace and tranquillity of it, and war for the aery projections of their giddied heads, as if Heaven and Earth were little enough to be mingled in the quarrel, tearing the ſeamleſs Coat of the holy Jeſus in pieces, cauſing Diviſions
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:44571:16"/> and Schiſms, that our holy Mother the Church is forced to utter her unwelcome voice, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſaid to <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, What thou my Son?</hi> But we are of a ſtrange diſpoſition, we uſe not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the Sun or Moon till we ſee them in Eclipſe, <hi>Lunâ non aſpicimus niſi la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borante,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca.</hi> And that courſe of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> with his Auditors beſt ſuits with our Natures, before we are ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour'd with this holy concord, we muſt be acquainted with its oppoſite vices<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>It is a Rule in Logick,</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traria juxta ſe poſita magis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luceſcunt.</note>. And a little knowledge in Judicial Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy will ſerve the turn to predict the ill effects of the Serpents teeth diviſion. An eaſie Obſervation can foreſee and foretel the ſad Events of excentrick Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and inteſtine Wars. Peace and Unity, like light and fruitful ſhowres, deſcend from above, from Heaven, from God; but ſtrifes and diſſentions, like tempeſtuous Vapours and fiery Exhala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, come from the Earth, from the devilliſh hearts, deſigns and practices of men. The Orator ſaid well, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Any raſh hand or furious head may inflict a wound, or kindle a fire, but it is God alone who can heal up the breaches of a Church or State. Private grudges and contentions (like ſeveral
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:44571:16"/> Cards in a Map, whoſe Lines are drawn infinitely croſſing, cut and thwart each other) muſt needs ſhew us the way to publick calamity. When humane Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties become Cannibals to one another, the bands of love, which hold Mankind to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, muſt neceſſarily be diſſolv'd, and we can't but behold a very ſad Landskip of horrour and confuſion, becauſe ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities and diviſions feed on envy and malice ſo long, till they break forth into a conſuming fire, in ruine and deſolation by an open Hoſtility. The Earth grows wild and becomes a great Foreſt of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage and cruel Monſters, and Mankind turns Beaſts of prey one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. When our united Force ſhould encounter <hi>Babylon</hi> the common Enemy<note n="*" place="margin">Cum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba foret Babylon ſpolianda tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaeis. <hi>Lucan.</hi>
                  </note>, we weaken our ſelves like thoſe ancient <hi>Romans</hi> by mutual diſſentions, and periſh by our own oppoſitions. If Chriſtians would but take the Moraliſts counſel, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to ſpend and derive their malice ſome other way; for many had rather employ their time in picking and feeding quarrels in the Church at home, than advance the unity of the Faith abroad; and how can any expect ſecurity from their enemies, while they are at variance thus with themſelves? Do any hope to eſcape the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:44571:17"/> fury of Aliens, while they are ready to ſheath their Swords in each others bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els?<note place="margin">Eph. 4.3.</note> S. <hi>Paul,</hi> that great Patriot of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and glorious Angel upon Earth, perſwades all to keep <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace.</hi> And if he hath but reaſon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to make him a man, and ſo much Religion as will name him Chriſtian, I doubt not but he will hearken to S. <hi>Peters</hi> advice,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.11.</note> 
                  <hi>to ſeek peace and enſue it:</hi> And will follow that which makes for peace, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> would have us;<note place="margin">Rom. 14.19.</note> for whether it be a ſecurity from open Invaſions, or an immunity from home-bred Oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, it is <hi>dulce nomen pacis,</hi> even to them that know no more of it beſides its name. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is a comprehenſive term, and ſignifies all proſperity or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward happineſs in the Hebrew ſtile; or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> peace from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to knit, being as 'twere the tye of mens affections; in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe reſpects, 'tis a thing delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, under any notion it is amiable and lovely, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Nazianzen.</hi> It is a kind of ſweet, divine and heavenly concent, harmony or beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of things ſubordinate one to another. In the oeconomy of Nature unity or peace is the combination of Creatures; by ſymbolical qualities ſo contempered and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:44571:17"/> diſpoſed by the will and pleaſure of the All-wiſe Creator, that all agree to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect harmony of the Univerſe to make up one intire body, the World. In the leſſer Worlds of mixt Bodies, peace or unity is the equal balance, or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> due moderation and temper of humors and parts, which keep their true place and proportion; <hi>Quâ quodlibet corpus non minùs appetit unitatem ſuam quàm Entita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem;</hi> therefore it preſerves Unity as its Being. In the Political World the State, peace or unity is the ſetling and due or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of things by juſt Laws of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo that Laws and Government are the Charter of our Lives and Liberty, the Pillar and Baſis of States and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and Cement of all Societies; for the whole deſign of Civil Power or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is to procure the private and publick happineſs of Mankind, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve men in their Rights, againſt the inſolent Uſurpations and Outrages of murders, perjuries, fraud and violence, and ſuch like miſdemeanors as would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade the World with Anarchy and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, and bring the Politick Body to confuſion. There is no one thing, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion excepted, that more ſecures and adorns the State than Juſtice<note n="*" place="margin">Jus &amp; aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas vincula ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitatum. <hi>Cic. Parad.</hi>
                  </note> doth. It is both <hi>Columna &amp; Corona Reipublicae</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:44571:18"/> (ſaith a Reverend Father of the Church) a prop to make it ſubſiſt firm in it ſelf,<note place="margin">Pietas &amp; juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia duo ſulcra Reipub. columnae regni. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi non eſt pudor, nec cura juris, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitas, pietas, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, inſtabile regnum eſt. <hi>As is well obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedian.</hi>
                  </note> and as a Crown to render it glorious in the eyes of others. Truth, Order and Juſtice are the only foundations of Peace and Unity in Church and State. In the rational World as men, (who are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, rational and ſociable Creatures) Unity is the conjunction of every mans powers and faculties in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf compoſing one individual inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and then concurring to a general union of wills and affections; for Truth is but one, as the Center, and draws all minds to an unity which tend to it. In the ſpiritual World, as Chriſtians, the Church is not a name of diviſion, but of unity and concord<note n="*" place="margin">Ibi non eſt Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia, ubi non eſt unanimitas. <hi>Eraſm. Paraph. in Act. 1.</hi>
                  </note>, being conjoyned together in one Communion and Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip in the myſtical Body of Chriſt. And we can't be joyned to Chriſt our Head, except we be glued with charity one to another. For he that is not of this Unity, is not of the Church of Chriſt, which is a Congregation or Unity toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and not a Diviſion. The Churches unity, which is by one Spirit from one Head, is but one in all: and though many Members,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.15, 16.</note> yet but <hi>one Body.</hi> As <hi>Gregory</hi>
                  <note n="‖" place="margin">Gregor. Mor. l. <hi>19.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> ſpeaks, <hi>Sancta Eccleſia ſic conſiſtit in uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate fidelium, ſicut corpus noſtrum unitum
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:44571:18"/> eſt compage membrorum.</hi> In the ſtructure of the natural Body all its parts conſpire for the good and benefit of the whole. There's ſuch a Symmetry and propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as that the Members are joyn'd by Nerves, Veins, Arteries and Ligaments to their Head, from whence they receive ſtrength and ſenſation, and by virtue of this union to the Head, retain a Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Community among themſelves: So it is in the Body Politick, the King's Majeſty the Golden Head of our Land, the Honourable Council the Eyes of it, the Nobles, Lords and Barons the Shields and Shoulders thereof, the Reverend Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Clergy the Chariots and Horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> the Tongues of the Land, the Judges (thoſe grave Sages) the Hands of our Land for the Execution of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, the flower of our Gentry and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons the Feet of our Land, Head, Eyes, Tongues, Shoulders, Hands, Feet: all, even all ſhould concur for the general good and publick ſafety, and in both for Gods Glory and Worſhip, that we may lead peaceable and quiet lives in all godlineſs and honeſty, becauſe peace is the foundation of happineſs, and luſtre of any Government, and the fierceſt Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of peace is diſſention in Religion; therefore unanimity is a work worthy of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:44571:19"/> every ones beſt endeavours, and of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute neceſſity to the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>bene eſſe</hi> of the Church, it is the Life and Soul of it; <hi>Eccleſia nomen eſt conſensûs &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiae.</hi> And that multiplication of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.6.</note> 
                  <hi>one Spirit, one Hope, one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm, one God and Father of us all,</hi> declare that we ſhould be all of one mind in the Lord, all keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace. It is a good thing when Unity and Concord, Peace and Religion go hand in hand, two gentle Companions as full of love as they are of innocence; and it is a great pity, that two of ſo near alliance ſhould ſuffer ever an injury of a Divorce, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine their deſcent, the root of both ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies to bind. Religion is a bond be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and man. Peace is a tye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween man and man, Chriſtian and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. And one would think the very name of Chriſtian ſhould have a greater efficacy and power to ſtill and ſuppreſs diſorders in the Church, than that of <hi>Quirites</hi> was preſently to huſh and allay the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in <hi>Caeſars</hi> Army; becauſe the Church is a ſpiritual Building made up of Souls, cemented with love, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſpeaks: It is a Body compact and knit together in one and the ſame Orthodoxal
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:44571:19"/> Verity, which was once given to the Saints in the holy Apoſtles days, and in all Subſtantials maintained by the holy primitive Fathers, for which we ought, as S. <hi>Jude</hi> tell us, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to contend earneſtly, even all that owne and profeſs the ſame Faith in ſincerity. The irratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal prejudice of many Schiſmatical Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries againſt the preſent Diſcipline would ſoon be removed, if they do impartially weigh the purity and ſimplicity of the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> A Church that teaches no other Doctrine but what Chriſt and his Apoſtles deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, derives none of its Principles from the impure Fountain of vain and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Tradition; but a <hi>ſure word of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy</hi> is that Spring that ſends forth all her Doctrines: So that all her Articles, all the parts of her Worſhip, all her Canons and Conſtitutions are by derivation pure and holy. Add unto this the innocency and decency of her Ceremonies, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity and Decorum in her Offices and Adminiſtrations, the integrity and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of her Manners and Principles. It holds no Tenets, nor teaches<note n="*" place="margin">Lib. Can. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcip. Eccl. Angl. &amp; injunct. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin. Eliz. Anno Domin. <hi>1571.</hi> Can. de Concio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natoribus.</note> any thing pernicious to Salvation, or diſſentaneous to the rule of Faith, in purity of life and holineſs of converſation, every way conſonant to the Doctrine and Diſcipline
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:44571:20"/> of primitive times in the firſt and pureſt Ages of the Church. And what Faith can be the foundation of a more ſolid peace, the ſurer Ligaments of Catholick Communion, or the firmer Baſis of a holy Life, and of the hopes of Heaven hereafter, than the meaſures which the holy primitive Church did hold, and we after them? Therefore we may conclude the Religion of our Church certainly Primitive and Apoſtolick, and the beſt Tranſcript and Original Copy of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity that is left in the World. And there needs no better demonſtration for bringing of men into the unity of Faith, and the knowledge of the Son of God, or eſtabliſhing a Community among us, than purity of Doctrine and of Worſhip in the Service of God by Prayers<note n="*" place="margin">The Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or publick Form of Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, though contemned and depraved by its malicious Adverſaries (out of a Spirit of contradiction and ſingularity, who do preach or ſpeak perverſe things againſt the Diſcipline and Government of our Church, out of their own Fanatical aſſeverations, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſaith S. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil,</hi> and the novel imaginations of their own brains) yet it is notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding religious and holy, and recommends to us the wiſdom and ſimplicity, purity and ſpirituality of Chriſtian devotion. It is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound of Texts of Scripture, exhortations to repentance, Pſalms, Hymns, Doxologies, Leſſons and Creeds. Forms for the Adminiſtrations of the holy Sacraments, Comminations againſt impenitent ſinners, all mixed and diverſified with great care to quicken attention, and ſtir up devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>, Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Sacramental Celebrations, which are the great characters and confirmation of true Chriſtians Communion with the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:44571:20"/> bleſſed and glorious Trinity, with God, with their Saviour, and the holy Spirit, and by the Grace of theſe with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for the holy Word of God, the Scripture of the Old and New Teſtament which ſtream from the Fountain of our Saviour, is the only Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard<note n="*" place="margin">The Authority of the holy Scripture, for which it ought to be believed and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed, dependeth not upon the Teſtimony of any man or Church, but wholly upon God, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19, 21. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.9. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.13. (who is Truth it ſelf) the Author thereof, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the Supreme Judge by which all Controverſies of Religion are to be determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and all Decrees of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, Opinions of ancient Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Doctrines of men, and private Spirits are to be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, and in whoſe ſentence we are to reſt, can be no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but the holy Spirit in the Scripture, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.29, 31. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.20. with <hi>Acts</hi> 28.25.</note> of true Religion both in Doctrine and Devotion, the foundations of Faith, and the ſuperſtructures of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, by an humble obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, holy fervency, and una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous harmony. For a ſweet Chorus of well-tun'd affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons will cauſe the goodly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of the Church to go up with the voice of Euchariſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.46, 47. ſhoutings and acclamations of joy, till it comes to the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of eternal happineſs and top of its ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual glory. And there is no outward Conſervative of Eccleſiaſtical or Civil peace comparable to that of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Religion, ſaith a Reverend Prelate, whoſe Orb or Sphere is true Doctrine, its Center holy Devotion, and its Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference good Government, which Bleſſing we enjoy by Divine Providence under our pious and religious Soveraign
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:44571:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> King <hi>Charles,</hi> for which all good Subjects and Loyal Proteſtants ſay, <hi>O King, live for ever.</hi> God grant Sedition may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a ſtranger in the Kingdom, and <hi>England</hi> be an object of emulation of all foreign States in the admiration of her glory, and the Proteſtant and Reformed Religion become the praiſe of the whole Earth in an univerſal agreement in the publick Worſhip of Almighty God. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing better ſuits with Chriſtianity, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more graces it, being like thoſe good people in the <hi>Acts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chap. 4.32.</note> of one mind, and one Soul. To oblige us to this god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly union and concord, arguments may be drawn from the alliance of humane Nature, and bands of a ſpiritual Conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinity. Firſt, we all ſprung from one <hi>Original,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 3.20.</note> one Blood derived through ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Chanels,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 17.26.</note> one ſubſtance by miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous efficacy of the Divine Benediction multiplied or dilated into ſeveral times and places. We are all fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioned<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Ariſt.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Greg. Naz.</p>
                  </note> after the likeneſs of our Maker, bearing the impreſſes of the Almighty; for the Soul is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a branch of a Deity. We all conſpire in the ſame eſſential Ingredients, being of one Compoſition<note n="‖" place="margin">Cogita iſtum, quem ſervum tuum vocas, ex eiſdem ortum ſeminibus, eodem frui coelo, ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>què ſpirare, aequè vivere, aequè mori. <hi>Senec.</hi>
                  </note> and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:44571:21"/> conſtitution; knowing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we all came from one, we ſhould love as one<note n="*" place="margin">Dilectio ſola diſcernit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter filios Dei, &amp; filios Diaboli. <hi>Aug. 1. Joh. Tract. 5.</hi>
                  </note>, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t dum cognoſcerent ſe ab uno eſſe omnes, ſe quaſi unum amarent,</hi> ſaith the Maſter of the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences. It is a heavenly Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date, the fruit of the Spirit is Love<note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Greg. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>z.</note>, wherein the Image of God, the power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and the Spirit of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity truly do conſiſt<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi odium, ibi charitas eſſe non poteſt; ubi charitas ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, ibi nil boni. <hi>Aug. ſuper Matth.</hi>
                  </note>. Love as Brethren, ſaith S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> and Logick can teach us, <hi>Relationes non egent locali con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tactu,</hi> Relative reſpects need not the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and touch of parties, then as many as are ſcatter'd in the remoteſt Regions, whether maſſacred in the <hi>Indies,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtrappado'd among <hi>Turks,</hi> or in that Hell of Torments, the Inquiſition of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> though they live in as divers places as perſecutions; yet if they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form with us in Orthodox Profeſſion, no diſtance can hinder their being our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, neither can their mean eſtates take away our tye of reference, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 'tis not the place,<note place="margin">Coelum non ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum mutat, qui trans mare cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</note> but quality of the perſons that cauſeth the unity of their affections. Though <hi>Joſeph</hi> be ſold into <hi>Egypt,</hi> and there lye manacled in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:44571:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> the injurious Priſon, yet he ceaſeth not to be <hi>Jacobs</hi> Son. <hi>Jonathan</hi> and <hi>David</hi> were ſtill Brethren, and faithfully united, when one was in the Cave, and the other at Court. Methinks <hi>Abrahams</hi> prudential motive to <hi>Lot,</hi> to win him to a Treaty of Peace, is an argument to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian World,<note place="margin">Gen. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>we are Brethren.</hi> Strifes and Emulations might quickly be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, if we did not forget the alliance of humane Nature. Though ſometimes the fierceſt are united, and ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Brethren; but it is with <hi>Jacobs</hi> addition, <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> Brethren in iniquity. The Prince which rules in the Air makes uſe of every ſtratagem to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large the Territories of his Kingdom, and he doth it upon this conſideration, his time is as ſhort as his Chain; therefore to be in readineſs at all hands, he hath his <hi>unitatem farmoroſorum,</hi> as S. <hi>Bernard</hi> calls them, a Confederacy of zealous Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that vow their furtherance at every diſplay of the Devils Enſign. Satan hath enjoyed in all Ages the unhappy benefit of ſuch peremptory aſſiſtants. Were that Kingdom of Darkneſs once divided, our Saviour aſſures us, it could not long ſtand; therefore the Head ſtudies to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve unity in the Members. Theſe are that Combination in <hi>Gregory Nazianzen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:44571:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> whoſe agreeing malice knits their hearts, and their conjoyned hearts unite their voice. If infernal Spirits are provident to maintain outward peace, where there is no order, but all confuſion, leſt their Kingdom ſhould come to an end, this conſideration ſhould engage the moſt unnatural oppoſites of this Land (who are Proteſtants bred up in the Principles of the ſame Religion, and walking in the Houſe of God as Friends) not to be teez'd on to as deadly feuds, as between a Jew and Samaritan. They are moſt odious Chriſtians who put on the glory of an Angel in outward profeſſion, that they may play the Devil more unobſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly; therefore let us labour to bring as much wiſdom and courage to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front, as the Devils Agents cunning and malice to undermine the Kingdom of Chriſt Jeſus, and glory of Chriſtianity; then for ſhame, let us be, if not Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, yet men; if not ruled by Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet perſwaded by Reaſon, that we had need, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts us, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to ſtrive together with a full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of all our might, and combine in a holy Faction to withſtand the fury of their united oppoſition. For how can it chuſe but diſparage our Cauſe, if jarring diſcord diſperſe our Forces? And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:44571:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> while we divide our ſelves, our Enemies in the mean time divide our ſpoils.<note place="margin">Bodin. Rep. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 'Tis regiſtred in Story, That <hi>Mars</hi> had in old <hi>Rome</hi> certain Prieſts cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Salii,</hi> it was their office when Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were together by the ears, to caſt fire among them and confound their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; therefore Antiquity named them <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Fire-bearing Prieſts. Who knows not that our modern <hi>Rome</hi> is as well furniſht for ſuch a Stratagem? and that this fire might be Veſtal, and never go out: ſhe hath bequeath'd unto the World a Society of Prieſts, whom ſhe intends for State-Salamanders, that ſhould live in the fire of other mens contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and by a ſlight of hand bandy it from one Kingdom to another. They carry with them fierce Bulls, ſuch as the Poet doth mention, <hi>Vulcanum naribus af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flant,</hi> and breathe or ſpeak nothing but in the fiery accents of deſolation; of which temper the Jeſuitick Spirit ſeems to be which deceives the Nations with the Cup of Errour, ſetting out Truths in a painted and meretricious Bravery, nay blending them with humane inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, teaching for Doctrines the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of men. And there can be no greater Sacriledge in the World, than to put our own Image upon the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:44571:23"/>(1.) Our Lord and Saviour hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us to read the <hi>holy Scripture,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 5.39.</note> and the Holy Ghoſt bleſſeth them that <hi>delight therein.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 1.</note> But the Roman Church forbids the reading thereof to the Laity in the vulgar Tongue<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <p>Haereſin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſe, ſi quis dicit neceſſarium eſſe ut Scripturae in vulgares linguas convertan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Sander. Viſib. Monar. lib. 7.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Credo inſtitutum hoc à Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolo eſſe inventum. <hi>Pereſ. de Trad. part. 1. aſſert. 3. pag. 47.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note>, which, if they ſhould be permitted the peruſal of, would eaſily diſcover their new Articles of Faith to be erroneous, their Image-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to be Idolatry, and their not erring Biſhop to be a grand Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. Pope <hi>Clement</hi> VIII. in the Index of prohibited Books ſays, That the Bible publiſhed in vulgar Tongues ought not to be read and retained, no not ſo much as a Compendium or Hiſtory of it. And <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſays, That it is not neceſſary to Salvation to believe that there are any Scriptures at all written. This is to blot out the Canonical Scripture, and give us Apocrypha in the room of it, to make the Divine Oracles to ſpeak to the patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizing of their own intereſt, and would ſuborn God for a Witneſs to their Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours. As <hi>Caligula</hi> dealt with <hi>Jupiters</hi> Statue, taking off the head of it, and placing his own in its ſtead: So they ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute the devices of their own Brain in the place of Gods Word, putting that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:44571:24"/> moſt excellent Candle under a buſhel, to make the Decretals of the Pope as au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick as holy Writ, and wholly rely on the Dictates of the Prieſt, ſetting more by an old Tradition, than a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Precept. Thus theſe inſolent Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, who ſeek not ſo much to oppreſs the bodies, as exerciſe their Tyranny o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Souls of men, and pitifully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thral them to everlaſting ſervitude. As the wicked Shepherds of <hi>Midian</hi> would drive their Neighbours flocks from the watering Troughs, and the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> would ſtop the Patriarchs Wells: So the Emiſſaries of <hi>Rome</hi> uſe all Arts to keep the people from the uſe of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, the Wells of Salvation, hindering them from inſtruction. It is a great glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that the Bible<note n="*" place="margin">The difference between Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the Fifth, and <hi>Clement</hi> the Eighth, the one commanding one Bible only to be uſed, the other ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, under their Curſes; whereby the Romiſh Partiſans are involved into a miſerable neceſſity, being conſtrained not to read any, or be liable to the Anathema of Pope <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> if they uſe <hi>Sixtus</hi>'s Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; or of <hi>Sixtus,</hi> if they uſe <hi>Clement</hi>'s.</note>, which was ſhut up in an unknown Tongue from the generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is now in our own Mother-tongue, and Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Kingdom. And what S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſpake of old concerning the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Iſlands, is verified at this day, every where a man may hear the people diſcourſing of the Scriptures, ſtrangers indeed in ſpeech,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:44571:24"/> yet of the Houſhold of Faith, in tongue Barbarians, but in converſation drawing nearer unto Saints; for the Chriſtian Laity in the <hi>Britannick</hi> Church (which is not permitted in the <hi>Roman</hi>) walk in the moſt clear Light of the Goſpel, and drink their fill of the pure ſtreams of the water of Life in Scripture<note n="*" place="margin">It is a weighty Saying of <hi>Tertullian, Adoro pl nit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dinem Scripturarum;</hi> for all Scripture was given by Divine Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 2 <hi>Tim</hi> 3.16. and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> for doctrine, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> for redargution, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> for correction, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> for inſtruction, that the man of God may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected unto all good works.</note>. And we all have not only li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty by Proclamation to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy it, but ſeveral Acts of Parliament to confirm our uſe of it, Religion and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy. God grant that which is ſo great a mercy and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to us, we make it not our miſery, by turning the cauſe of our thankſgiving into murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, repining and diſſatisfaction; for if ever Times were under croſs and unluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Aſpects, if ever there were a publick Spirit of Phrenſie and miſchief in the World, certainly this Lot is fallen upon ours, in contending for Mint and Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, diſagreeing in the leſſer<note n="‖" place="margin">Diſunanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and diſuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity are a breaking not only of the King's but of God's and the Churches peace. It cauſeth diſtraction, hinders devotion, and indiſpoſeth men unto Religion, and clouds the underſtanding in the diſquiſition of Truth, and conſequently hinders that bleſſed light which clarifies the Soul of man, and prediſpoſeth it unto the brightneſs of eternal felicity.</note> only, when they all agree in the ſubſtance and in the greater as matters of Faith and Articles of Belief, <hi>viz.</hi> to believe in the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, one Divinity of equal
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:44571:25"/> Majeſty in the holy Trinity. It were to be heartily wiſh'd, that in matters that truly concern ſo much the glory of God, the honour, peace and welfare of the Church and Commonweal, that all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicate Opinions (varniſh'd with plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible errour through pride and ambition) might be laid aſide, and in the zeal of affection not forget our Duty, and the Unity that ſhould be among Chriſtians.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) Chriſt adminiſtred to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples both Species of the Sacrament of Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, and his Command ſtands in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Record,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.27.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>drink ye all of this,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark 14.23.</note> and <hi>they all drank of it,</hi> ſaith the Canon of Scripture. Chriſt ordains it, but the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> forbids it, as if they were wiſer than our Saviour, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their mouths againſt Heaven, and correcting his holy and divine Inſtitution. For in the Council of <hi>Conſtance</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Et ſimiliter. quod licèt in primitiva Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia hujuſmodi Sacramentum reciperetur à fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delibus ſub utra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſpecie; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men haec conſuetudo ad evitandum aliqua pericula &amp; ſcandala, eſt rationa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliter introducta, quod à conficientibus, ſub utraque specie, &amp; Laicis tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tummodo ſub una ſpecie ſuſcipiatur, &amp;c. <hi>Conſt. Seſſ. 13.</hi>
                  </note>, they alter'd the Teſtamental Legacy and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Chriſt himſelf, in taking away from the Laicks the Chalice of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the holy Symbol of Chriſts Blood,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:44571:25"/> ſtiled by the Apoſtle, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Cup of Bleſſing; for the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſtical Elements are not Theories or empty Signs, but Seals to confirm, and Inſtruments to exhibit Chriſt with all the benefits of his Paſſion, and bleſſings of Heaven unto every believing Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; therefore the Romiſh Church does great injury to Chriſtendom in her half Communion, the deprivation of the Chalice. <hi>Quomodo Teſtamentum nuncu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant, qui mortem Teſtatoris negant? Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo libertatem uſurpant, qui negant ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinem, quo redempti ſunt?</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ambroſ. ep. <hi>73.</hi> lib. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſays, That he who receives the Myſtery otherwiſe than Chriſt appointed, <hi>i. e.</hi> in one kind, when Chriſt has appointed two, is unworthy of the Lord, and he cannot have devotion. Its innovation and novelty is clearly manifeſt, if we look into the Glaſs of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, <hi>but from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it was not ſo</hi>
                  <note n="‖" place="margin">Mat. 19.8. See the Reverend Dr. <hi>Pierce</hi> in his primitive Rule of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</note> (as our Saviour ſaid of Divorce) which is a ſufficient confutation. <hi>Caſſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Eccleſia Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entalis in hunc uſque diem; Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentalis verò ſive Romana mille amplius annis continuis, non aliter quàm ſub duplici specie in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventu Eccleſiae Sacramentum hoc Dominici corporis &amp; ſanguinis admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraſſe, legitur, &amp;c. <hi>Conſult. de utra<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Spec.</hi>
                  </note> ſays, That the Eaſtern Church to this day, and the Weſtern or Roman Church, for more than a thouſand years,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:44571:26"/> did exhibit the Sacrament in both Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to all the Members of Chriſts Church. S. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, one Body and one Cup is given to all.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Calixtus</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Peractâ conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratione, omnes communicent, qui noluerint Eccleſiaſticis carere homini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus; ſic autem etiam Apoſtoli ſtatuerunt, &amp; Sancta Romana tenet Eccleſia. <hi>De Conſecrat. diſt. cap. 2.</hi>
                  </note> ſpeaks fully, When the Conſecration is finiſh'd, let all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate that will not be thruſt from the bounds of the Church; for ſo the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles appointed, and ſo the holy Church of <hi>Rome</hi> does hold.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Gelaſius</hi>
                  <note n="‖" place="margin">Comperimus quòd quidam, ſumptâ tantummodo corporis ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cri portione, à calice ſacri cruoris abſtineant: Qui (pro culdubio, quoniam neſcio quâ ſuperſtitione docentur aſtricti) aut integra Sacramenta perci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piant, aut ab integris arcean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quod diviſio unius ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> myſterii ſine grandi non ſit ſacrilegio. <hi>De Conſ. diſt. cap. 2.</hi>
                  </note>, Some taking (ſaith he) a portion only of the ſacred Body, do abſtain from the Chalice of the ſacred Blood. I know not by what Superſtition they are obliged, let them either receive the intire Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, or be kept from the whole, becauſe the diviſion of one and the ſame Myſtery cannot be without grand Sacriledge. Nothing can be a greater cauſe of wonder and amazement in the conſideration of it, than that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould ſeek to obſcure the light of Truth, ſhining as clearly as the Sun in its Meridian beauty and ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, arrogating to themſelves a Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:44571:26"/> over our Faith, and introducing ſuch Doctrines and Practices as are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Rules of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, and the pureſt Ages of the Church. As Lawgivers, ſetting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves down in S. <hi>Peters</hi> Chair, as they pretend, and magiſterially decree<note n="*" place="margin">Si quis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xerit ex Dei praecepto, vel de neceſſitate ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis eſſe, omnes &amp; ſingulos Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti fideles, u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tram<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſpeciem Euchariſtiae ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mere debere, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathema ſit. <hi>Concil. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. Seſſ. 5. Can 1.</hi>
                  </note> Laws and Conſtitutions diametrically op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the Divine command, and Chriſts holy Inſtitution. When the Lamp of Reaſon is darkened and obſcured, the Soul preſently embraces a cloud, and courts a ſhadow, the blackeſt errours and moſt palpable wickedneſs muſt needs cover the face of thoſe Souls that ſtart back and apoſtatize from their God, and their Reaſon. To preſerve therefore its lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre and integrity in the memories of all thoſe who bear any true love to ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Truth, the ancient Light eſtabliſh'd and receiv'd in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is a ſecure Guide to direct us, not to be weary of old Truths, forſaking the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent paths to eſpouſe new and fond Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; that we neither incline to the cunningly compoſed Charms of Popery on one hand, or ignorant<note n="‖" place="margin">The Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts have been playing at Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, and the Government and Hierarchy are the Balls they toſs. The Separatiſt ſtrikes them into the Popes Hazard, calling them Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Prelacy. The Papiſt with vehemence rackets them back again as Schiſmatical (but the Roman Church are the Schiſmaticks in renouncing al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> communion with all Chriſtian Churches in the World, except their o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>) and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l it is with us, which ſoever wins the game. The one b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>s down the wall of <hi>Sion,</hi> by diſturbing the peace of the Reformed C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ch; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he other builds up the ruines of <hi>Babylon</hi> in ſuperſtitious Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> And they are ſo faſt linked and tied together (like <hi>Samſons</hi> F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>) with Fire-brands of Sedition, that if they be not quenched by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r of Majeſty, they can't chuſe (when the means are fitted to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Plot) but ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t the Church on fire, and the State in an uproar.</note> Sectarians, and men of unſtable minds on the other, who crumbling into Conventicles, are
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:44571:27"/> ready to joyn with every Enthuſiaſtick Sect, and ſo making Gods <hi>Iſrael</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a <hi>ſpeckled Bird</hi> of ſeveral colours,<note place="margin">Jer. 12.9.</note> of all varieties of Religion. S. <hi>Paul</hi> has a term for them,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.8.</note> if they like it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, men of ſick brains, as well as of corrupt minds. And ſuch is the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogant diſpoſition of ſome tranſported humors, being under the torrid Zone of unruly paſſion, that rather than they will acknowledge their errours (though never ſo apparent) the very State and Law it ſelf muſt be condemn'd, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcend to their diſtempers, being led more by their own pleaſing Fancies than right Reaſon, or the ſacred Rules of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Truth, who have laboured to ſow the Tares of Diſſention in the Vineyard of the Lord, diſquieting the Unity of Gods Church. Diviſion is the only mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical note that ſounds harmoniouſly in the ears of our <hi>Zimries.</hi> And it is a Truth undeniable, That theſe later times have produced a doleful Scene of various
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:44571:27"/> tranſactions, and conſequently diſcover'd and brought to light the unparalell'd de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns and execrable intentions of Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical zeal, or Democratical fury; for the Diſſenters in this Age have conſpir'd together to untye the knot of Chriſtian Charity, and produce an unhappy Schiſm in the Church; what elſe mean thoſe ſtrange whiſpers, myſterious workings, and grand plotting, who would not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uncover the roof, and take down the Pyramids and Battlements of venerable Epiſcopacy, but like the rough Sons of <hi>Edom,</hi> raze it even to the ground? And under hypocritical diſguiſes contrive the ſad prodigy of Treaſon, whereby we ſee that Apoſtates to Atheiſm, and Revol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to Schiſm are Monſters of ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, or Fiends incarnate (who could imagine miſchief againſt ſo much Mercy, and ſin againſt ſo great Goodneſs) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiting the Protection of a gracious Prince with traiterous Machinations<note n="*" place="margin">See His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy againſt his Sacred Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, read in all Churches and Chappels within this Kingdom, <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptemb.</hi> 9. 1683.</note>, and under the mask and ſpecious preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Religion bring to ruine the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Kingdom, as it is by Law eſtabliſh'd in Church and State. Loyalty, like freſh and fragrant odours, breathes forth ſweetneſs in the noſtrils of all thoſe who hold Fidelity to the Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter to be the beſt cognizance for the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:44571:28"/> Coat of a Subject. But for the ungodly Principles and bloody Practices of impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable men and barbarous Miſcreants plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting unnatural and helliſh Conſpiracies againſt the Perſon, Crown, and Dignity of Sacred Majeſty, let them be as <hi>Oreb</hi> and <hi>Zeb, Zeba</hi> and <hi>Zalmana</hi> that periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or elſe remain as <hi>Pilate</hi> in the Creed a curſe to all poſterity. Diſcontented Pride has made more Schiſmaticks than Conſcience; if this hath ſlain its thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, that hath killed its ten thouſands. Many are zealouſly affected to Truth, but for want of ſound knowledge, or meek and humble hearts, they are full of violence, their capacities are over-caſt with a cloud of ignorance, that intercepts their view, and blunts the point of the brighteſt ray their underſtanding ſends forth to diſcover any Errour of the Church, but breaks out in a clamorous ſtorm of paſſion<note n="*" place="margin">Clamoris ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na doctrina Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticorum, quae non in ſenſu, ſed in multiloquio &amp; clamore ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatur. <hi>S. Hieron.</hi>
                  </note>. Here I may recite the words of S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> againſt the Letters of <hi>Petilian</hi> the Donatiſt, changing <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelium</hi> into <hi>Eccleſia quae mitiùs pertuli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Regum flammas;</hi> The Church better en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dured the flames of Tyrants, than the tongues of Schiſmaticks. <hi>Nam illis in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cendentibus unitas manſit, vobis loquenti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bus manere non potuit;</hi> for while the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> burned, Unity remained; but while theſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:44571:28"/> rail, the Church muſt needs be divided; for Schiſms and Diviſions ſet up the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Satan, the Prince and ſubtle Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of the Air, the potent Adverſary of Mankind, who holds his Supremacy and Dominion by Variance and Enmity, and all his Agents ſubordinate to him, <hi>Nihil ſpeì niſi per diſcordias habent,</hi> as <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſpeaks. No Logick or Reaſon can batter down the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſtrong Holds of prepoſſeſſed falſe Opinions, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the determination of general Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, nor unanimous conſent of Primitive Traditions; nay the Scripture it ſelf muſt ſtrike Sail to their Judgments, as if the Oracle of the Word would only admit of their corrupt Gloſſes and falſe Annotations, which <hi>Irenaeus</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Adverſ. Haereſ. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>43.</hi>
                  </note> joyns together, <hi>ſcindentes, &amp; elatos, &amp; ſibi placentes,</hi> Schiſmaticks, proud<note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mater omnium Haeretico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſuperbia.</hi> Aug. de Gen. contr. Manich. l. 2. c. 8.</note> and ſelf-pleaſing men. This was one of the Originals of <hi>Arrius</hi> his curſed Hereſie, his pride and envy againſt <hi>Alexander</hi> the good Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> as <hi>Theodoret</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Theodor. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Hiſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> reports. <hi>Pelagius</hi> alſo and his Aſſociates, who though they did acknowledge the name of Grace<note n="‖" place="margin">Gratiae voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulo frangens invidiam, offenſionem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> declinans. <hi>Aug. de Grat. Chriſt. l. 1. c. 37.</hi>
                  </note>, to decline envy, and avoid
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:44571:29"/> the curſe of the great Council of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage,</hi> yet ſtill they did but ſhelter their proud Hereſies under Equivocations and Ambiguities. What ſtore of this Coin is minted at <hi>Rome,</hi> to advance and ſupport the Grandeur and Greatneſs of the Papal Monarchy (who dams up the clear wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Antiquity<note n="*" place="margin">The Reverend Biſhop <hi>Taylor</hi> in his Diſſwaſive from Popery, <hi>pag.</hi> 124. ſaith, The Roman Emiſſaries endeavour to prevail amongſt the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and prejudicate by boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Antiquity, and calling their Religion, the old Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the Catholick: So by inſnaring others by ignorant words in which is no truth, their Religion, as it diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhes from the Religion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neither the old nor the Catholick Religion, but new and ſuperinduc'd by Arts known to all who with ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and diligence have look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into their pretences.</note>, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens the ſluce to the puddles of Novelty) is viſible by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences and Pardons, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated Grains, and Prayers for the Dead. Pope<note n="‖" place="margin">Primus indulgentiarum nundinas, primus in Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium extendit indulgentias. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grip. de Vanit. Scientiarum, cap. 61.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> VIII. (who lived in the Reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt of <hi>England</hi>) was the firſt that inſtituted the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe or Sale of Pardons, and extended them to Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory; for the Doctrine of Purgatory is the Mother of Indulgences. The vaſt Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure iſſuing<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sixtus</hi> the Fourth was wont to ſay, <hi>Papae non deerunt pecuniae quamdiu ipſi manus erunt &amp; calamus;</hi> The Pope could never want money ſo long as his hand could hold a pen.</note> thence is ſolely poſſeſſed by the Pope, and no other Patriarch in the World. It is a matter of meer intereſt and advantage, and if theſe Silver Shrines were not, the Crafts-men of <hi>Rome</hi> would quickly fall. If there were no gain (ſaith a
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:44571:29"/> Reverend Prelate) to be reaped from them, their chief Champions would be aſhamed of the great <hi>Diana</hi> that they worſhip. When the Truth of God, and the Death of Chriſt, the Kingdom of Heaven, and the Fire of Hell, the Souls of Men, and Salvation of the World, ſhall be made baſely ſerviceable and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributary to the boundleſs pride and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of the Pontificality and See of <hi>Rome,</hi> who ſeeks to abuſe Antiquity, and to patronize their own Errours, ſubject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Religion into Maxims of humane Policy<note n="*" place="margin">All their Policy tends to maintain their archieved Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty and Greatneſs, whereby his Holineſs ſhall be eſtated not only in the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> but alſo in the Seigniory of the whole Weſt, not <hi>in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualibus</hi> only, as Vicarial Head, but alſo Lord Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount <hi>in Temporalibus,</hi> as Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch of the Church, in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving all power upon Earth at his will, and the Crowns of Kings to ſtand or fall at his pleaſure.</note>, and the ancient in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of the Apoſtolick Faith into Innovations and a new Belief, as <hi>Gregory Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzen</hi>
                  <note n="‖" place="margin">Gregor. Nazian. Orat. in Arianos.</note> ſaid of the <hi>Arians</hi> their refined Doctrines, meer Novelties, new-broach'd He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies. For at the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> they adjoyn'd new Articles of Faith to thoſe twelve which the Apoſtles ſet down for a ſufficient Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary of ſound Doctrine, whilſt the Sacrifice of Maſs, Corporeity of Preſence, the Doctrine of Purgatory, Invocation of Saints, Worſhip of Images, and the like, were commanded to be embraced and received with the ſame
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:44571:30"/> pious affection and reverence as the holy Scripture, under no leſs penalty than Damnation, and to be believed for fear of Anathema.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>O Roma<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Rome</hi> once the Emporium of the World, and Mart of Chriſtian Faith, when it enjoyed all the happineſs this life is capable of, it grew exorbitant. That State which ſeem'd above foreign caſualty, laboured with its own happineſs, and from its height and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry found way to ebb again:
<q>
                           <l>Roma diu titubans variis erroribus acta</l>
                           <l>Corruet, &amp; mundi deſinet eſſe caput.</l>
                        </q>
                     </note> à Româ quantum mutata vetuſtâ es?</l>
                  <l>Nunc caput es ſcelerum, quae caput orbis eras.</l>
               </q>
               <p>For a Nation or People to receive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity and true Faith from Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf or the Apoſtles, matters nothing, unleſs they do ſtill retain the ſame Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical and Divine Principles. Some can talk over the ſeries and deſcent of all times, with ſuch a perfum'd breath, and richneſs of Language, as if they were made with the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> ſpeak of the Dictates of the Patriarchs, and Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the Prophets; but in vain do any boaſt they are deſcended from <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſince he is not a Jew who is one outward in the fleſh, bur inward in the Spirit, as our Saviour told the Phariſees vaunting of <hi>Antiquity,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 8.</note> except they did the works of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and abide in the Truth. Truth then is the Child of Time; and as there is Antiquity of Time, ſo alſo of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:44571:30"/> Truth and Doctrine. And ſo long as the Romiſh Church continued in the profeſſion and practice of Apoſtolical purity, <hi>i. e.</hi> of Faith and Doctrine which was once given to the Saints, all other Chriſtian Churches held Communion with her; for the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> did not anciently, in former Ages, hold all theſe Doctrines which now ſhe owns. The ancient Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was but a Member of the Catholick Church of God, of which Jeſus Chriſt was Head: But the now Roman Church does (at this day) what S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">De <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nit. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. cap. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> told to the Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, incloſe the Catholick Church with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their own circuits, and uſurps it whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to her ſelf, of which the Pope is Head. And the Papacy will have their Pope, by reaſon of the Kingdom of Chriſt, to be the Head and King of the Church <hi>in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine ad Spiritualia,</hi> and conſequently the Supreme Civil Power over the Monarchs of the Earth <hi>in ordine ad Temporalia,</hi> to be the Head and King of the Church. Such a Church was never in <hi>Rome;</hi> for many hundred years after our Saviour, no Biſhop<note n="‖" place="margin">Gregory <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of</hi> Rome: Ego fidenter di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co, quia quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis ſe univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem Sacerdotem vocat, vel vocari deſiderat, in elatione ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>â Antichriſtum praecurrit. <hi>Pope</hi> Pelagius diſtinct. <hi>99.</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſalis autem nec etiam Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus Pontifex appelletur. Cyril <hi>Patriarch of</hi> Conſtantinople: <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> did aſſume Chriſts Title to be the Head of the Church, till <hi>Boniface</hi> the Third, who not contenting himſelf
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:44571:31"/> with his Juriſdiction Eccleſiaſtical, and fulneſs of Spiritual Power, but his towr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ambition aſpires yet higher, and with much contention obtained of the Rebel <hi>Phocas</hi> about the year 604. (who mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd <hi>Maurice</hi> the Emperour) the Title of Univerſal. The Pope looking for Primacy on Earth, is very unlike his heavenly Maſter, whoſe Vicar he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to be. Chriſt paid Tribute unto <hi>Caeſar;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 20.25.</note> but the Pope, that Prevaricator of the Apoſtolick See, exacts it from them, and <hi>Caeſar</hi> pays unto him. Our Saviour waſh'd his Diſciples feet; but the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> (in theſe days) with imaginary Supremacy cauſes the greateſt Princes, and mightieſt Emperors do him Homage and ſwear Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Clement</hi> the Fifth call'd a Council at <hi>Vienna, An.</hi> 1311. in which it was ordained and decreed, That the Emperour his Lord ſhould give his Oath of Allegiance to the Pope; for being not content with his Primacy, abuſed Religion into Policy; and caſting off all moderation, the Pope de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured the Emperour. Thus the Head of the Church de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated into a Monſter, and in reaching at Temporal Soveraignty, he broke the Spiritual Unity.</note>, contrary to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Authority and Majeſty of the Scripture, <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the higher powers, Rom.</hi> 13. and <hi>to the King as Supreme,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. As Heathen <hi>Rome</hi> under the Emperours, <hi>Domitian</hi> and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:44571:31"/> others, would be adored as Gods, though never ſo impious: ſo <hi>Rome</hi> Chriſtian falls under the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the Apoſtle, <hi>Sitting in the Temple of God as God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.4.</note> 
                  <hi>and exalting himſelf above all that is called God</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Zacharias Papa ex autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate Sancti Petri Apoſtoli mandat populo Francorum, ut Pepinus qui poteſtate Regiâ u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebatur, etiam nominis digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate frueretur. Ita Hildericus ultimus Merovingorum, qui Francis imperabat, depoſitus eſt, &amp; in monaſterio miſſus eſt.</hi> Marian. Scot. Hiſt. lib. 3.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Lambertus Danaeus</hi> in his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſe to <hi>Bellarmine</hi> the great Maſter of Controverſie, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending that <hi>Childerick</hi> was lawfully depoſed by Pope <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charias:</hi> Can <hi>Zachary</hi> (ſaith he) have Authority in <hi>France,</hi> being a Stranger? Can he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the publick Magiſtrate, being but a private perſon? (though he were Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi>) or transfer that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipality to <hi>Pepin,</hi> that he hath no Right unto? and commit ſo many Sacriledges and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties, ſtealing from <hi>Childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi> and giving to <hi>Pepin</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans Right? Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Subjects to violate their Oaths, which they had ſworn to their King? Tranſpoſing Kingdoms from one man to another, whereas it doth only belong to God to depoſe Kings, and diſpoſe of Kingdoms? Thou mayeſt ſee <hi>(Bellarmine)</hi> how many outrages this thy <hi>Zachary</hi> hath committed. <hi>Reſp. Danae. ad Bellar. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 17. <hi>pag.</hi> 316.</p>
                  </note> in a ſuperla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Greatneſs, and that not of order and precedency on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as to Eccleſiaſtical Regen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, ſtretching his Dioceſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all Biſhops and Churches in the Chriſtian World, but of abſolute Authority, claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing univerſal Juriſdiction in a Monarchi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al Superinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency or Regality over all Chriſtendom, with a Power to depoſe Kings, and diſpoſe of Crowns and Kingdoms for the benefit of the Church, is a Title only of Uſurpation without any ground of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture or Antiquity. Firſt, Chriſt was no Temporal Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, but an Eternal King to reſcue us from the thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of ſin, the ſorcery of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:44571:32"/> the fleſh, and the Curſe of the Law. Chriſt was no earthly King, and left no Regal Power to S. <hi>Peter;</hi> therefore the Pope can have no Civil Power or Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Dominion as the Vicegerent of Chriſt, and conſequently overturns and deſtroys the Doctrine of Supremacy. The Lawgiver himſelf, even <hi>Ipſe Ille,</hi> that bare rule in Heaven, the incarnate and crucified Meſſias,<note place="margin">Joh. 12.36.</note> ſaith, <hi>My Kingdom is not of this World.</hi> Whereas that Sect of Politicians, the Romaniſts, turns the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt into outward Pomp and Bravery, and they to have the Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Government of it, as if the now See of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould be known to be the moſt Chriſtian Biſhop, not in having with Chriſt no Temporalties, but an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Soveraignty to depoſe Kings, and diſpoſe of Kingdoms, which is nothing leſs than a ſtrange Uſurpation; for the Son of God did never impoſe ſuch a hard duty and condition to Kings that were to become Chriſtians, as to forſake their Imperial Crowns and Diadems, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in their hearts and affections, and in compariſon of the Kingdom of God. O Eternal Word, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Light of Truth, inſpire the Univerſal Church with the Spirit of Truth, Unity and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and grant that all they that do
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:44571:32"/> confeſs thy holy Name, may agree in the Truth of thy holy Word, and live in unity and godly love. Secondly, View it in relation to the Apoſtles, who were the Patriarchs of the Church. And the Evangeliſts make ſpecial mention of their Names, as thoſe to whom we owe great honour and veneration, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant with Chriſt, and daily inſtructed by him, who continued with him unto his Paſſion and Crucifixion; and after his Reſurrection he applied himſelf eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to them, to enable them for the high Myſteries of the Goſpel, and ſervice of the Church by the <hi>reception of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 20.22, 23. Mat. 18.18.</note> and a power of binding and looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſins. And Chriſt having founded his Church, he left it in the hands of his Apoſtles; therefore let us look into this pure ſtream of Antiquity, and primitive Age of the Church.</p>
               <p>In the firſt Synod there is no prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of one, or ſubordination of another, but all the Apoſtles have equal vote and choice in the Subſtitution or Election of <hi>Matthias.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>In that other about Circumciſion, all decree, ſend and judge alike,<note place="margin">Acts 15.</note> 
                  <hi>It ſeemed good to the Holy Ghoſt and us.</hi> By which it is evident, there is no Preeminence or Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority, but an Unity and Identity of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:44571:33"/> Power, according to that excellent Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of S. <hi>Cyprian</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Hoc erant uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que caeteri Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoli, quod fuit Petrus, pari con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſortio praediti &amp; honoris &amp; pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatis, ſed exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium ab unitate profici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>citur. <hi>Lib. de Unit. Eccleſ.</hi>
                  </note>, The other Apoſtles are the ſame that S. <hi>Peter</hi> was, to let us know, that they and their Succeſſors are <hi>pari authoritate, pari conſortio,</hi> endowed with an equal fellowſhip of honour and power.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtles now conſidered in their Apoſtolical dignity, order of Prieſthood, and Authority of Preaching, the light will diſplay it ſelf, and chaſe away the darkneſs from us.</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) In Apoſtolick Dignity then is no Principality by the Law of Chriſt; for as they were all ſent <hi>together,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 10. Acts 2.</note> ſo they were all inſpired at <hi>once,</hi> the cloven Tongues like as of fire ſate on each of them, and they were all filled with the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, which argues equality, and that they are all Fellow-equals in Apoſtleſhip.<note place="margin">Rev. 12.14.</note> 
                  <hi>The wall of the City,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>John, had twelve foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ions, and in them the Names of the Lamb</hi>'s twelve Apoſtles, therefore no Primacy or preeminence of dignity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Foundations of Evangelical Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, upon which the height of the Eccleſiaſtical Edifice is raiſed, and Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Church is built. They are all Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations and Rocks after Chriſt, becauſe they were all choſen to preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:44571:33"/> and plant the Faith in every part of the World. They were all imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately inſtructed by Chriſt; they had all moſt ample and univerſal Juriſdiction throughout the whole Empire of the Church; all endowed with an equal Authority, as S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> expreſſeth it, of honour and power, which beats down the Rampire of defence, and ſhews the Fortreſs of folly of the Romaniſts in their new erected Fort, in challenging a Scepter of Supremacy, and condemns the arrogant Uſurpation of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> who will be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Biſhop in another mans Dioceſe, and in appropriating that to himſelf, which is common to him, ſaith a Reverend Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, with all the Biſhops of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) As to the Order of Prieſthood, there is no Supremacy of power to one above another in the Colledge of the Apoſtles, becauſe they could all equally conſecrate the Body and Blood of Chriſt. And the greateſt favours to lapſed Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind are the Sacraments, where the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble corporeal Elements are the means by Faith to convey unto us ſpiritual Graces; nay, the whole Treaſure of Chriſts Merits, acquired on the Croſs, are made truly ours by a due reception of the bleſſed
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:44571:34"/> Euchariſt; for the holy Sacraments are the pledge of Glory, and earneſt of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, and the conſecrated Symbols are the ſeeds of an eternal Duration, ſpringing up in us to Life eternal, nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing our ſpirits with Grace, which is but the Prologue of Glory. In the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Myſteries there is no Superiority as to Conſecration, it being not perſonal, but publick, not proper to S. <hi>Peter</hi> only, but common to all the Apoſtles, and conſequently ſpeaks an equal fellowſhip of honour and power as to order of Prieſthood.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) As to the Authority of Preaching, the Commiſſion is equal,<note place="margin">Joh. 17.18.</note> 
                  <hi>As my Father ſent me, ſo ſend I you,</hi> which may extend not only to Juriſdiction and Ordination, but Apoſtolical preaching. Our Lord and Saviour being to aſcend into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, commanded his Apoſtles, ſaying, <hi>Go ye teach all Nations,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 28.19.</note> 
                  <hi>baptizing them in the Name of the</hi> (Sacred Trinity) <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</hi> This com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment they put in execution, and it was fulfilled,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Their ſound went into all the Earth, and their words into the ends of the World:</hi> S. <hi>Peter</hi> to the Jews, S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the Gentiles, no diviſion or limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Juriſdiction, but a diſtribution to all Provinces, for the more commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:44571:34"/> preaching of the Goſpel. Thoſe ancient Worthies that firſt propagated Chriſtianity, had neither Dioceſe nor Pariſh, but the wide World before them: then, all planting the ſame Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, every man had a care of all the Churches, they went forth and preached every where,<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <p>Mark 16.20.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Euſebius</hi> and other Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Hiſtorians give us the recital and ſpecification of the Nations and Countries. S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> preach'd in <hi>Judea, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch, Galatia, Cappadocia, Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> in <hi>Aſia, Bithynia</hi> and <hi>Rome.</hi> S. <hi>Andrew</hi> in <hi>Scythia, Europaea,</hi> in <hi>Epirus, Thracia</hi> and <hi>Achaia.</hi> S. <hi>James</hi> the Son of <hi>Zebedee</hi> in <hi>Judea</hi> and <hi>Spain.</hi> S. <hi>John</hi> in <hi>Judea</hi> and <hi>Aſia</hi> the leſs. S. <hi>James</hi> the Brother of our Lord in <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> S. <hi>Philip</hi> in <hi>Scythia</hi> and <hi>Phrygia.</hi> S. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomew</hi> in the farther <hi>India</hi> and <hi>Armenia</hi> the great. S. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> in <hi>Ethiopia.</hi> S. <hi>Thomas</hi> to the <hi>Parthians, Medes, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, Brachmans, Hyrcanians, Bactrians</hi> and <hi>Indians.</hi> S. <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> in <hi>Meſopotamia.</hi> S. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias</hi> in the higher <hi>Aethiopia.</hi> And S. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> in many Countries of <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Aſia.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>the Lord working with them.</hi> What mean now theſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineering <hi>Nimrods</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> abſolutely out of the pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of their Power to lord it over their Brethren, as if they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſpecially <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Gods portion and inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and all Chriſtian Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches were in a ſtate of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination unto them? where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they are only Fellow-la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers and Workers toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with us in the Vineyard of Chriſt. <hi>Are ye Miniſters of Chriſt? ſo are we.</hi> The Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy are Branches of an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical and holy Stock; therefore let all <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Sons, who aſcend the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and are devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Altar as Gods Prieſts, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate themſelves to God and Religion, that we and they may do the work of an
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:44571:35"/> Evangeliſt, and with alacrity and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, give our ſelves to prayer and the miniſtration of the Word, ſhewing the Divinity of our Function not in great ſwelling words of vanity, in an affected Predominancy, Rule, and Superiority over the Chriſtian World, ſo much contended for by the Souldiers of the Camp of <hi>Rome.</hi> This in the words of <hi>Nazianzen</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Nazian. Orat. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note>, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to commend a goodly Statue from the ſhadow it caſts, and to paſs by <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, thoſe perfections which deſerve our chief commendations, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſanctity and holineſs of life which extol Gods praiſes, and then are we <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, living Laws and Royal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of greatneſs to the World, when we do and ſpeak <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſo as not to diſgrace, but adorn the Goſpel, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently ſtop the mouths of all gainſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, by a controuling ſanctity of actions, and all men be wholly convinced or compelled to unity and obedience. It is expected then, whatever habits are in faſhion among others, that the Prieſts ſhould be cloathed with righteouſneſs, adorn'd with a decent converſation, and produce the fruits of good works, theſe be the evidences of the Buds, Bloſſoms and Almonds of <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Rod, and denote
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:44571:35"/> its Supremacy. Nothing will reſtore the Church (ſays a Reverend Prelate) to its priſtine honour, love, and authority in mens hearts and minds, but a ſerious ſetting themſelves to the ſtudy, preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and practiſing of truth and peace in a holy life. Theſe were the Arts, theſe the Policies, theſe the pious Stratagems by which anciently they gained peoples hearts to love God, his Truth, and of themſelves the witneſs of it, to ſuch a height of honour and ecſtaſie of love, that they received them as the Angels of God, and Ambaſſadors from Heaven. God grant the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> may be like <hi>Jacob</hi>'s <hi>Ladder,</hi> which he ſaw in <hi>Bethel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 28.12.</note> whereon were Angels aſcending and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending: ſo by our Office and Miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Angels might in us aſcend and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry up ours and the peoples ſupplications unto God, and Angels by us deſcend to bring Gods Word and Meſſage to the people, that there may be the ſweet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texture or agreement of Beings, one eſpouſed to another in faithfulneſs and truth, even a bleſſed Union betwixt Prince and People, and a gracious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord too of the people among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (in an united conformity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction in the Service of God) being knit together in the inviolable bonds of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:44571:36"/> Loyalty and love, neither entoiled with Civil broils within, nor infected with Hoſtile inroads from without; but all profeſſing that one eternal Truth, (which is both the Mother and Nurſe of Peace) we may enjoy ſuch a tranquillity as in the days of <hi>Solomon,</hi> when <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> dwelt ſafely every one under his Vine, and under his Fig-tree, from <hi>Dan</hi> even to <hi>Beerſhaba.</hi> Or as it was in the days of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> when there was ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence in Heaven for the ſpace of half an hour, and the prayers of the Saints aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up as a cloud in grateful odors. The prime perfection then and pleaſure in this life (ſecond to that ſupernatual one, Faith in Chriſt, and Sanctification through the Spirit) conſiſts in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding Brethren to dwell together in unity, which limns and ſhadows out the glorious Hierarchy of Heaven, the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in Unity, for <hi>Deus eſt unitas &amp; omnis unitatis affector</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Dionyſ. Areop.</note>; let us therefore expreſs this unſpeakable concord by the Sacrifice of our ſelves to a Spirit of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Truth, and not a Spirit of Error and Diviſion, which cauſeth the breach of Union, the diſturbance of the Peace, and quiet of the Church. As the unity of Faith joyns us, ſo the bond of Charity tyeth us faſt together through one and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:44571:36"/> the ſame Spirit to unity and godly love, becauſe Schiſm is the next way to Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, which is to be hated as a thing that leads to deſtruction: And <hi>non ſemper ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatur unitas in credendo, ubi non eſt uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas in colendo;</hi> there will not always be unity of Doctrine in that Church, where there is not uniformity of Diſcipline. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Writers can tell us, by concord the weakeſt<note n="*" place="margin">The Sun-beams diſperſt are but of ſmall force, but they gather ſtrength, if col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected in a narrow glaſs. <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurus</hi> the Scythian on his death-bed (as ſtory tells us) taught his fourſcore Sons the force of Unity by a Faggot of Rods; or, as it is in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> a bundle of ſhafts, while to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, are hardly broken; but if you divide them, 'tis quickly done. And thus it is in <hi>Eccleſiae faſciculo, Hoſea</hi> propheſieth deſtruction, but this doth uſher it in, <hi>Their hearts are divided,</hi> Hoſ. 10.2.</note> things grow ſtrong, by diſcord the mightieſt States are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown. Though States dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, the Communion of Saints muſt be preſerv'd, the Church ſhould keep at unity, and by united force repel Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. After all our unhappy Diviſions, what can be more ſeaſonable to the Genius of our Times, than cementing counſel? that all Gods Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may be raiſed up as of one ſtone, by having <hi>cor unum &amp; viam unam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 32.39.</note> 
                  <hi>one heart and one way,</hi> which was the Character of the Church, Chriſtians <hi>primitive Age;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 4.32.</note> for Diviſion is a ſad Prognoſtick threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning deſolation, when the ſtones of the building begin to fall off from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the houſe grows ruinous,<note place="margin">Iſa. 30.13.</note> 
                  <hi>and the breach thereof comes ſuddenly in a moment.</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:44571:37"/> May the number of thoſe increaſe that are friends of <hi>Sion,</hi> and the generation of thoſe periſh that make it their deſign to lay waſte the City of God, and bury her in her own ruines: Did the godly Jews mourn for <hi>Judah?</hi> And ſhall not the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation for the Land of our deſires and Nativity? O that ever ſuch an inlightned <hi>Goſhen</hi> ſhould hatch or har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſuch black Monſters, that would gnaw out the bowels of their own Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther! That ſo many <hi>Judaſſes</hi> ſhould be found amongſt Chriſts Diſciples! The Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Iſa. 15.5. Chap. 16.7, 9, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>My heart ſhall cry for Moab, and bewail the vine of Sibmah: I will water thee with my tears, O Heſhbon, and my bowels ſhall ſound like a harp for Kirhareſh.</hi> Is not <hi>England</hi> as dear unto us? and have not we as great cauſe to lament for this Church and State, the Womb that bare us, and the Breaſts that gave us ſuck? Every one ought to bow down, and go heavily as one that mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for his mother, by reaſon of her Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions<note n="*" place="margin">No Church ſo fair in this World, as to be without ſpot and wrinkle; none ſo happy, as to be wholly priviledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from jarrs and diſſentions. The Jewiſh Church in Chriſts time was full of diviſions, there were Phariſees, Sadducees, Eſſenes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the Church of <hi>Philippi,</hi> what conteſtations and tumults, broils and factions were there? and that not Oeconomical about <hi>meum</hi> and <hi>tuum,</hi> but Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical, and in matters of Religion by thoſe of the Conciſion, thoſe evil workers, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls them. In the flouriſhing Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> where there were ſo many Chriſtians of the firſt magnitude, eminent for Religion and Piety; yet even here are ſtrifes and diviſions, inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as S. <hi>Paul</hi> wrote his firſt Epiſtle to diſſolve thoſe factions, and repreſs thoſe diſſentions that were amongſt them. In the Church of <hi>England</hi> (to come home to our ſelves) there is Presbyterian, Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, Anabaptiſt, and Quaker; and it may be ſaid of our days, as in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s time at <hi>Corinth, There are diviſions among us.</hi> In Paradiſe there was <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, only in Heaven there's <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, full and perfect harmony without any diſcord, but we can't look for a Church triumphant here below.</note>. What ſcandalous and irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Libels of factious Brains have been
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:44571:37"/> expoſed to the publick view of all <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Gazers? What indiſcreet and Saty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Pamphlets have been diſperſed by a malevolent Party to incite a diſlike and hatred of the Government in Church and State? For <hi>Sions</hi> ſake then I cannot hold my peace, but deplore the decay of Religion by the want of Union and Loyalty, and the defect of the practice of this ancient and heavenly Duty of Unanimity amongſt us. Our Saviour left to his Church the Legacy of <hi>Peace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 14.27.</note> it is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, his Farewel gift, or, as S. <hi>Baſil</hi> calls it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a largeſs dropt from a higher World, worth the keeping; therefore let us (in our ſeveral ſtations) endeavour the unity of the Spirit, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in the bond of peace, beating down all animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, ſtudy of Parties, and obſtinacy in Opinions, which breeds diſaffection, and this humor grows impetuous<note n="*" place="margin">Animi in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammati ebul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liunt ad certa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note>, march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like <hi>Jehu,</hi> the Son of <hi>Nimſhi,</hi> furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:44571:38"/> till it flames into open contention, giving to the reſtleſs Emiſſaries<note n="*" place="margin">Whatever the pretenſions of <hi>Rome</hi> are to love and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord among themſelves, yet their want of unity appears in their different Opinions, Schiſms, cruel Wars, and in the conteſts between their Popes, and Acts of their Councils contradicting one another. Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> in his Tract of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſets down 300 differences of Opinions, maintained in the Popiſh Church, recited by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelf, the Arch-pillar of the Roman Synagogue. The many Schiſms in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> may be eaſily conjectured, when there were ſeveral Popes at the ſame time, one fought againſt another, and the greateſt Conquerour wore the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Crown. The people were wofully divided, and many thouſands of Chriſtians were ſlain in thoſe bloody Battels between Pope <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> and Pope <hi>Clement.</hi> This Schiſm continued almoſt fifty years, one reſident at <hi>Rome,</hi> another at <hi>Avignon.</hi> The want of concord and unity in the See of <hi>Rome</hi> is alſo demonſtrable in their cruel Wars between the Popes and Emperours, called <hi>Bellum Pontificum;</hi> whereby all <hi>Europe</hi> at one time or another has been divided by Feuds and Factions. And the Popes not only thundred out their Excommunications againſt the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, but alſo perſwading their own Subjects to levy War againſt them, as if Chriſt had ordained his Sacraments, not to be Seals of Grace, and helps of our Faith, but hooks to catch Kingdoms, and rods to ſcourge ſuch Potentates as would not, or could not procure the Popes favour, and conſequently has embroiled the Chriſtian World in diſcord and diſſention, in great and cruel Wars. It is a thankleſs work in the ſight of God to improve his Worſhip by the dint of the Sword, and to found his Church, as <hi>Romulus</hi> did <hi>Rome,</hi> in blood. No ſuch Sacrifices, no ſuch Ambages of cruelty can be acceptable to the God of mercy and Prince of peace and pity. The bitter contention and envy of one Pope to another, ſpeaks their privation or want of unity, one diſannulling all the Acts of another, as Pope <hi>Stephen</hi> VI. abrogated all the Decrees of his Predeceſſor <hi>Formoſus,</hi> and ſo of many others. The like appears in their Councils, contradicting one another; the Council of <hi>Baſil</hi> decreed for the Council againſt the Pope, and the Council of <hi>Lateran</hi> under <hi>Leo</hi> X. decreed for the Pope againſt the Council. The Council of <hi>Toledo</hi> did prohibit the Worſhip of Images; the ſecond Council of <hi>Nice</hi> commands it. And ſo our Adverſaries of <hi>Rome,</hi> who boaſt of intire Unity, may ſee their own vanity.</note> of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and growing Sectaries, great advantage, and to Satan no ſmall
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:44571:38"/> occaſion to laugh and triumph. It were well for us, if we would ſee or ſuſpect the policy of the Devil, or his Agents, who envy our happineſs, and take ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage either of our judgments depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, or Natures corrupted, to make us their inſtruments to break our bleſſed unity in Church or State. And ſo while we are contending for ſhadows, we may be deprived of the ſubſtance, and be brought into irrecoverable confuſion; therefore let brotherly love and unity be maintained in the World, ſtanding faſt in one Spirit, with one mind for the Faith of the Goſpel<note n="*" place="margin">It is one evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Truth of the Chriſtian Religion, that Chriſt hath carried it on by means contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble againſt all oppoſitions imaginable. Who could have thought, that a few illiterate Fiſhermen that had neither skill in Grammar, or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in Rhetorick, ſhould carry on the Truth in a Majeſtick ſimplicity? The Princes of the Earth being not only non-aſſiſtants, but all the great Monarchs of the World oppoſing Chriſtianity in the infancy thereof, whilſt it was in the cradle, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.26, 27. King <hi>Herod</hi>'s enraged jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie burned ſo fiercely, that it ſucked up the blood of all the male-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants within the Coaſts of <hi>Bethlehem.</hi> And had not an heavenly inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion diverted the Eaſtern <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> from the intended way of their return, their blood alſo ſhould have run among the ingredients, and made up the doſe to allay the fury of an angry Prince. Add unto this thoſe fierce perſecutions continuing in their height and heat, with a rage reaching up to Heaven, for the ſpace of three hundred years, no ſtorms could blow out the light of this Sun, clouds might cover it, but never extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh it, becauſe the Goſpel is from God, the World cannot overthrow it, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.39. whereas all thoſe Religions which the Romans, Greeks, and all the Gentiles went a gadding after before the advent of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, are all come to nothing, and the reſt riſen ſince ſhall ſhortly be deſtroyed with the brightneſs of his coming, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.8. therefore ſtand faſt in an united conformity, ſtriving together for the Faith of the Goſpel.</note>, as Members of one
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:44571:39"/> Body under one Head, Jeſus Chriſt. Which leads me to the ſecond general: as the alliance of humane Nature, ſo the bands of a ſpiritual Conſanguinity en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gages us to holy concord.<note place="margin">Gal. 3.28.</note> 
                  <hi>We are all one in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Chriſt taught all alike to call God Father in the Lords Prayer. All have the ſame filial Prerogatives,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.26.</note> 
                  <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem above is the Mother of us all.</hi> All as one mans children have the ſame food provided them, like <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſuch as are brought up with the ſame milk,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.2.</note> the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as S. <hi>Peter</hi> calls it, <hi>of the Word.</hi> For all Chriſtians are Children of the ſame <hi>heavenly Father,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mal 2.10.</note> regenerated to the ſame <hi>lively hope,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.17.</note> 
                  <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heirs</hi> of the ſame heavenly Inheritance, redeemed by a Saviour that breathed out nothing but <hi>Love,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 63 9. Joh. 15 13.</note> ſanctified and ſealed by a Spirit of Unity. It is a Truth in the fourth of the <hi>Acts,</hi> there were many bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and but one Soul. I wiſh unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity may ſo combine<note n="*" place="margin">The language of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> to his Synod of Biſhops, has been applied by the Royal <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> our moſt gracious <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> to his Senate at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> or ſeveral Houſes of Parliament: <hi>I ſhall be as glad of your future <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, as now I am of your welcome Meeting.</hi>
                  </note> the people of this Realm, and knit together the hearts of this whole Nation, as the heart of one man, in the defence of our King, our Law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and our Religion, that (as <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> taught in his <hi>Ethicks</hi>) though they
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:44571:39"/> be many in Body, yet they'l be but one Soul, <hi>Crederes unam mentem in d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>bus fuiſſe diviſam,</hi> as 'twas between <hi>Minutius Felix</hi> and his <hi>Octavius.</hi> God grant 'em a Soul that's one in will, and one in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, one in reſolution, and one in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; for united Spirits graciouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorting together by a ſweet harmony of affections, tend not only to the glory of our <hi>Jeruſalem to be as a City that is at uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in it ſelf,</hi> but the Nature of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſpecially requires it, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thereof exacts it from us, becauſe the Lord our God is one Lord. This Unity is <hi>Oyntment which covering the head, and running down to the skirts,</hi> makes the Prince glorious, and the Subject hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py; for where it is, there <hi>the Lord hath commanded the bleſſing.</hi> As difference of Languages hindred the erection of <hi>Babel,</hi> ſo diſunion of minds the going forward of the ſecond Temple, whoſe founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is laid in Love. Surely <hi>Sion</hi> can as ill be built with diſcord of Hearts, as <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi> could with diſcord of Tongues. God is not wont to be in the Whirlwind of diſſention, but in the ſtill Voice, and that heavenly Dove, the Holy Ghoſt, like the Halcyon only, builds his Neſt in a calm. The garment of the Kings Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Church, is of divers colours,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:44571:40"/> though there be variety of Gifts, yet it ſhould be like Chriſt's Coat, without ſeam, <hi>in veſte varietas ſit, ſciſſura non ſit.</hi> Lines, the nearer they approach to the Center, the nearer they are to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; thoſe then are at the greateſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from God, who are furtheſt off from one another in uncharitable diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences. It was the great buſineſs of our Saviour's advent into the World, to make peace in Heaven and Earth, to reconcile men to God, and to one another, to take away all feuds, and to extinguiſh animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, to bring to an agreement Tempers moſt diſtant (ſaith a Learned Divine) to make the Lamb and the Wolf lye down together. He came not to kill and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, but for the healing of the Nations. When the glorious Temple was built at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> God would have but one Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar there, to ſhew, <hi>quòd unum eundem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> cultum inter omnes eſſe vellet;</hi> all that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed there ſhould have one and the ſame Worſhip, but one Altar typifying one Religion, one heart, and that it might be unto the people <hi>ut vinculum ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crae unitatis,</hi> a bond of ſacred union. And this is the nobleſt Argument that can poſſibly be diſcuſſed to compoſe diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and allay the animoſities, which particular reſpects, private intereſts, and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:44571:40"/> parties of Religion have raiſed among us, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to be of one mind in the Lord; for it is not enough, <hi>concordare,</hi> to agree, but we muſt, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venire,</hi> come together, and not only ſo, but <hi>conſentire,</hi> agree in Judgment, that we may be brought <hi>cohabitare,</hi> to dwell together in unity. O how happy a thing it is to ſee the Churches Children ſpread themſelves like Olive-branches round her Table in a peaceable and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing manner. Honour and Riches are inſenſibly multiplied upon a Nation that ſeeks its glory by a dutiful ſubmiſſion to its lawful Prince, while it looks upon Union as the beſt Accommodation and choiceſt Treaſure, the Heavens and Earth conſpire to make it plentiful and abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in all <hi>wealth</hi> and <hi>opulency.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 28.2, 3. 4, 5, 6.</note> As thoſe Pigeons then which having drunk of the River of Life, held up their Bill <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> joyntly together in token of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs: So let us all praiſe God with one accord in the Temple, being of one heart and one Soul, mind and judgment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>the Lord our God is one Lord.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 6.4. Mark 12.29.</note> And what the Idea of the World could not, the ſacred Pages and Volumes of holy Writ have diſcover'd of the Deity, the Co-eternity of the Son of God with the Father, the proceſſion of the Holy Ghoſt
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:44571:41"/> from both, the Unity of the three in one uncreated Eſſence;<note place="margin">1 Epiſt. Ch. 5. ver. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>For there are three that bear record in Heaven,</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>John) the Father, the Word and the Holy Ghoſt, and theſe three are one.</hi> Thou art my Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, my Redeemer and my Comforter, which makes the queſtion paſt all queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and needs no further diſputation, <hi>I have none in Heaven but thee.</hi> The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of this Celeſtial place and ſtate, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Royal Prophet to deſpiſe all tranſitory flaſhes and ſparks of earthly pleaſures, which is the ſecond part, <hi>viz.</hi> Low in a poſitive determination, <hi>And there is none upon Earth that I deſire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thee.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="72-128" type="pages">
               <p>The Princes and Monarchs of the World, who are retinued with all the Equipage of Greatneſs, and ſtrange va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of delights; being liberally and abundantly provided for; Silver, Gold, and Jewels are their's, and all Creatures in the Earth, and the Air and Water are preſſed for their ſervice: yet all theſe enjoyments are nothing without thee, <hi>None upon Earth I deſire beſides thee. Et tecum non,</hi> the negation is perſonal, no man for his favour, no Creature for its excellency that I deſire in the leaſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of thee. For the treaſures of this world are but gilded Thorns and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:44571:41"/> Miſeries; and yet how many Shrines and Altars are there erected in mens hearts to this great Idol of the World? Moſt ſcarce acknowledge any other God but this Golden Calf, to which they pay their ſervile devotions. And when thoughts ſtream towards wealth, Rivers are but draughts enough for them. <hi>Quod naturae ſatis eſt, homini non eſt,</hi> as <hi>Seneca,</hi> that grave Moraliſt, ſpeaks of <hi>Alexander,</hi> who had ſwallowed up <hi>Darius</hi> and the <hi>Indies,</hi> and yet in thoſe flouds did thirſt, and in that ſurfeit was hungry. If the Earth were a Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Diamonds, and did the Heavens ſhowre down Pearls into <hi>Diana</hi>'s lap; and could we enjoy the Land with its Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals of Gold, and the Sea with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of its Treaſure, ſending Ships to <hi>Tarſhiſh,</hi> and fetching Spices from the Eaſt in the Navy of <hi>Hiram;</hi> all theſe things can't ſatiate the deſires of the Soul, but are miſerable fruitions without the glorious Trinity. Then when others lay up on Earth, Heaven ſhall be my Treaſure. For the favour of a Prince is but a pleaſing ſnare without thee, and therefore <hi>non eſt in terris, there is none upon Earth I deſire beſides thee.</hi> The World is a Theatre of ſorrow, a warfare and a bondage, all are priſoners, ſome
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:44571:42"/> in golden Chains, others in Iron; ſome ſlaves to poverty, others to riches, ſome to honour, others to meanneſs: And all theſe are interwoven with mixt varieties, as pain and grief, pleaſure and ſadneſs; ſo that the greateſt happineſs that the world can afford, is not able to fill the unlimited deſires of the heart, but God only. For the world (the Fools Paradiſe) is full of Vipers, the obſcure print of unſound joys, a dream'd ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and a very Ocean of gall; and ſo <hi>there is nothing on Earth that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire beſides thee. Mundo utamur,</hi> uſe we may, but not adore the Creature; we may look upon fair this picture as the work of the Almighty, but not eſteem it for a Deity or a God, like the fooliſh Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, or thoſe Perſians that gave venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion only to the luſtre of their Jewels. The Chriſtian account (as to Divine <hi>Arithmetick</hi>) is caſt up for another world,<note place="margin">Pſal. 90.12.</note> to be a Denizen of the New <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> an Heir of <hi>Eden,</hi> a Peer of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, a Pearl of Vertue, a Star of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Although we are Sojourners here<note n="*" place="margin">A Chriſtians life is a meer pilgrimage, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. We are all ſtrangers and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims, therefore let your converſation be in Heaven; and well may I with S. <hi>Paul</hi> adviſe you ſo to do, becauſe it is the chiefeſt Principle in Chriſtianity; for as the Stars move in their ſeveral Orbs, and the Planets in their Circles, ſo a Chriſtians Sphere is above in Heaven, there he performs all his regular motions.</note>, however we are <hi>Muncipes Coeli,</hi> Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:44571:42"/> of Heaven, Inceptors in Happineſs, Probationers for Glory, and have the priviledge to be called and own'd by God as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Fellow-Citizens of the Saints; walk therefore worthy of this honourable City, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of you are Members, and worthy of the Parents from whom you deſcended, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſaith <hi>Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cydides</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Thucydid. l. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note>. A Chriſtian is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, one that lives in the Confines of Heaven; ſo that whilſt he is here on Earth, he wants but the courteous hand of Death to put him into poſſeſſion, and give Livery and Seiſin of that <hi>above.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.1.</note> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven then is my home, the Creator my Father, the Judge my Advocate, the Spirit my Conſolation; therefore <hi>there is nothing on Earth that I deſire beſides thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The oppoſition of Notes on both (being the ſecond general) now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> In primacy of Order, King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> is the glaſs in which we may behold Chriſtian practice. In his thoughts Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven takes the precedency of Earth, <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but thee, O Lord?</hi> This is his firſt care to ſeek <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Kingdom of God, here is the <hi>primum mobile</hi> that moves his heart, his will, and
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:44571:43"/> his affections, Heaven: then the deſire on Earth follows after; and it is honour enough for this vile Earth to wait upon Heaven. Let us not now chaffer Heaven for Earth (as ſottiſh Indians truck away Ore for glaſs) and for the gaudy nothing of this life, hazard our immortal Souls to everlaſting flames, and for the toyes and vanities of this world loſe an Eternal Kingdom, and for a glorious mortality bid adieu to Heaven, which ought to have the precedency in our heart and affection. Open our eyes, O Lord, that we may ſee thoſe glorious rayes that ſtream from the Divinity, and ſo beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful an object will be enough to draw and attract our hearts unto thee, echoing forth the Anthem of the Text, <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but thee? And there is none upon Earth that I deſire beſides thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Take it in the ſenſe of the Verbs, <hi>habeo &amp; deſideravi; habeo in Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, I have in Heaven; deſideravi in terris, I deſire on Earth.</hi> Here we tire our ſelves with a reſtleſs fancy, ſtill wandering through the Creation, but never finding any ſatisfaction; but in Heaven there are all things that may delight us, and ſolace the faculties of our Soul. For God is a plenitude of light to the underſtanding, a multitude of peace to the will, Eternal
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:44571:43"/> joy and conſolation to the memory. And in Heaven all our deſires ſhall be ſatisfied with fruition, and thoſe excellencies will always ſupply new and freſh deſires to the Soul, which in the beatifical viſion ſhall enlarge into that vaſt and infinite ſatisfaction, that it ſhall be loſt in the enjoyment, and moſt happily plunged in that fruition which we ſhall never ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtand, but be ſtill more and more happy in having pleaſures ſo great as to tranſcend our knowledge. How glorious is that Sun that ſets not! and how clear is that day that is not chaſed by the darkneſs of the night! Heaven is that reſplendent reſidence, and of this bliſs, there is ſuch a fulneſs, that our heads are too thick to underſtand it; or if we were able to underſtand it, yet our hearts are too narrow to give it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance; or if our hearts could hold it, yet our tongues are too ſtammering to expreſs and utter it<note n="*" place="margin">Mens deficit, vox ſilet, non mea tantùm, ſed &amp; Angelorum. <hi>S. Ambroſe.</hi>
                  </note>. If the Heaven were fuller of Stars than it is, and if this lower World were adorned and illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated with as many Lamps as 'tis capable of, yet would they never be able to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the abſence of one Sun. Neither can the ſons of men, with all their Lamps and Torches of Reaſon, make up the leaſt ſhadow of Glory, the leaſt appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:44571:44"/> of Heaven. There's ſuch depths, ſuch Pleonaſms, ſuch Oceans of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in a Deity, as it exceeds all intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual capacity; for it is ſuch, as eye hath not ſeen, ear heard, nor yet enter'd into the heart of man to conceive, what the Almighty, the great Being of Beings, hath prepar'd in Heaven for thoſe that fear him. And though ſome veſſels con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain more than others, yet all ſhall be full, there ſhall be no vacuity or want in any.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Take it in the diverſity of the prepoſitions, <hi>cum &amp; praeter,</hi> nothing with, nothing beſides thee, O Lord! Heap up all the riches of the world into one pile, till they reach the Stars, and charm all the delights of the world into one Circle, and enjoy them freely; yet there is a deſire in man, which looks a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove them; for <hi>whom have I in Heaven but thee? And there is nothing on Earth that I deſire beſides thee.</hi> The Organ of a Chriſtian Ear is not for Earth, its mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick is mixt with too many diſcords, 'tis Heaven it aims at, the Angels with whom it would conſort, and the melody of the ſuperiour powers that yields the moſt abſolute concord. This is the Pſaltery that King <hi>David</hi> ſings to, and is the true <hi>Ela</hi> of a Chriſtian; <hi>Whom have I in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:44571:44"/> but thee? And there is nothing on Earth I deſire beſides thee.</hi> How miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble are they then, whoſe pleaſures only divert them from <hi>God</hi> their Maker; and have no other Apology for their Neglect of Heaven, than what Sin can make? that court the World, and for a fading Embrace exchange a Diadem of Bliſs, a Crown of Glory?</p>
               <p>And here let us raiſe our Thoughts from Earth to Heaven, becauſe the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Trinity is a fairer Object for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation: For in the Glaſs of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity we may behold all Felicity; it will be joy to mans Soul, health to his body, beauty to his eyes, muſick to his ears, honey to his mouth, perfume to his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils, whole happineſs to every part. Therefore let us no longer doat upon this Mole-hill of Earth, or prize its arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial complexioned Pleaſures, Structures of Cedar and Vermilion, Garments and Embroideries of <hi>Aholiab,</hi> Tables of Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacies, Couches of Eaſe and Ivory; all things here below are but <hi>Bracteata Foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitas,</hi> Copper leav'd with Gold. If we do but behold the Pavement of Heaven ſtuck with Stars, as ſo many ſparkling Diamonds; how deſpicable and mean is the ſtatelieſt Palace of the greateſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch? If the Hangings be ſo precious,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:44571:45"/> what muſt we think of the Room? If the Frontiſpiece be ſo glorious, what are thoſe better parts yet unſeen? <hi>Magnum &amp; mirabile ſub tanta Majeſtate.</hi> O think then what Treaſures, what Riches, what Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies are in thoſe Courts above, where the Gates of the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> are beyond the Orient Majeſty of Pearl, and Streets more ſplendid than pure Gold; where there is no need of the clear Light of the <hi>Moon,</hi> nor the bright Beams of the <hi>Sun!</hi> What ineffable Glory is in <hi>God,</hi> the Light of thoſe heavenly Tabernacles? Conſider but the Eternal Joys of that place, and how heartleſs and dying is the beſt of worldly pleaſures? Nay, were the whole World turned into a Seraglio of Delight, and every Region into an <hi>Arabia;</hi> could every Field become a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, and every Object that we meet with, bring with it a Magazine of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; had we all the Enjoyments this Life could triumph in, yet without <hi>God</hi> we ſhould find them diſmal Fruitions. Heaven doth as far ſurmount all theſe things, as the Celeſtial Sphere doth this Earthly Globe. And ſo the Propoſition is made good, That Heaven is a fairer Object than Earth for our Contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, even the glorious and Eternal Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of the holy Trinity, that is enſhrin'd
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:44571:45"/> in an Unity of Eſſence. And <hi>Pythago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras,</hi> that old <hi>Samian</hi> Philoſopher, made Unity the Original of all Things, and the Cauſe of all Good in the World. And the Fathers under the Allegorical vail of that Unity, diſcover an undivided Deity, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as if That and <hi>God</hi> were ſo inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly linkt together, that the thought of man could not poſſibly part them aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. 'Tis a pious Exhortation that S. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ul</hi> gives the <hi>Epheſians</hi> to holy Concord and unity of Spirit;<note place="margin">Eph. 1.4.</note> and lays it down with a triple Argument, (knowing that a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold cord is not eaſily broken) and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of no ſeparation at all, unleſs they would ſeem to diſſolve their Religion: <hi>There is one Lord,</hi> whom Chriſtians obey, and therefore no diſtraction by ſervice; <hi>There is one Faith,</hi> whereby they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and therefore no diviſion by Creeds; <hi>There is one Baptiſm,</hi> whereby they get entrance into the Church, and therefore no diſtinction by initiative Grace: and theſe three are more pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that Trinity of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, wherein God by the Miniſtry of the holy Apoſtle, appears to his Church as it were in the ſhape of three Angels.</p>
               <p>Silence now, ye warbling Birds, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorts of the World be ſtill, and hear the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:44571:46"/> Harmony of the Royal Prophet ſung in an admirable Air, tune the Inſtruments of your hearts unto it, <hi>Thou art my por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, thou art my riches.</hi> I love the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of thine Houſe, which is no other than thine own Eſſence, and the ſole aim of my deſire is the place of thy Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. The Diadems and honours of this world are of a ſhort ſtanding, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing comparable to that Royalty which is everlaſting, and to that Kingdom which knows no end.</p>
               <p>This World is an Ark wherein are clean and unclean Beaſts; a Park where Goats and Sheep live together; a Net where good and bad Fiſh are found: But in Heaven nothing that is impure or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect can have entry there: In that fair place <hi>Solomon</hi>'s wiſdom will appear folly, his knowledge ignorance; <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom</hi>'s beauty ſhall be there deformity; <hi>Samſon</hi>'s ſtrength ſhall paſs there for fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs, and the riches of all the Kings of the Earth ſhall be there as poverty. The longeſt term of life in our Forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will appear a death; for in Heaven it is in triumph above the reach of dull mortality. A man may enjoy the light of the Sun, and walk in its glittering rayes, and now and then give a glance upon it, though we cannot keep our eye
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:44571:46"/> fix'd upon its globe to behold its glory; we may behold its beams refracted through a cloud, but we may loſe our ſight by gazing on it in its naked beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; for according to an Axiom in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, <hi>Excellens objectum laedit ſenſum. Pliny</hi> prying into the Mountain <hi>Veſuvius,</hi> to diſcover the fiery irruptions of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures Kiln, procured his death by his too bold attempts into the myſteries of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Surely it cannot but be dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to be too inquiſitive into the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Trinity, which ought rather to be religiouſly ador'd than curiouſly ſearch'd into, and requires not the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Opticks or Eye of Reaſon, but of Faith. Reaſon can't <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore delight in a demonſtration, than Faith does in reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Truth. As the Unity of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head is clear to the Eye of Reaſon, ſo the Trinity of Perſons, that is, three glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Relations in one God, is as certain to an Eye of Faith <hi>Faith is</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.1.</note> 
                  <hi>the evidence of things not ſeen,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. 'Tis an Eye that can behold an abſent Object. A hand that can faſten upon what is not, can graſp things in their firſt poſſibilities, and the bare will of the Deity to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce any thing, and gives us the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of that Theological and ſtupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:44571:47"/> Myſtery, even the Trinity in Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; or that the Deity, which is eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially one, is ſubſtantially three<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> Zanchy, de tribus Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him, &amp; uno Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hova, <hi>lib. 1 cap. 2.</hi>
                  </note>. The Soul impriſoned in a body, can but darkly conceive of ſpiritual Beings, thoſe that are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the greateſt apprehenſions, do but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, they have ſome broken and ſcatter'd notions, which can't repreſent heavenly Truths in their proper Species, ſo vaſt is the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion between Divine Myſteries and a finite Underſtanding; for humane Wit knows not things here below, how then can it be ſatisfied in the ſearch after Divinity? If he whom our Saviour cured of his blindneſs, ſaw men as trees walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in what ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e ſhall they diſcern Evangelical Truths, who have yet the ſcales upon their eyes? Now there is a Curtain drawn, if we are ſo bold to lift it up, we may juſtly be ſtruck with blindneſs, even in thoſe things which before were expoſed to our view. It is enough that God makes us of his Court, though not of his Council: That we may be free, though not to rifle his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet, yet to ſit at his Table, no matter whether on the right hand or left in his Kingdom. Why ſhould we ſtrive with danger, for what we may be ignorant of with ſafety? In ſuch things admiration
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:44571:47"/> is better piety than apprehenſion. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing breeds more Atheiſts among us than this (the firſt ſpawn of ſin) Curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, which plucks ſtill at the forbidden Tree. The Arminians will find a reaſon in us of Gods Decrees. The Socinians alſo will have a reaſon of his Myſteries, except they ſee, they will not believe. Our ſight now doth diſperſe and loſe it ſelf in the immenſity of the extent; for who hath beheld it, that he might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate it? Not the Angels, for they cover their faces, much leſs we that dwell in houſes of clay, and have that igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and guiltineſs thoſe glorious Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phims are freed from, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.2. that cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed one to another, and ſaid, <hi>Holy, holy, holy.</hi> One of the Ancients gloſſes finely upon it, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num Jehovam celebrant repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendo unum &amp; idem</hi> (Sanctus) <hi>trinum agnoſcunt ter repetendo quod uni tribue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt:</hi> A Trinity they acknowledge in that bleſſed Unity of the Godhead, whilſt they repeat thrice, <hi>Holy, holy, holy;</hi> three in one, and all three but one God. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Gods incommunicable Properties and Works have (though moſt unjuſtly) been attributed to falſe Gods, as Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity<note n="*" place="margin">O Pater, ô hominum, divum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> aeterna poteſias. <hi>Virg. Aen.</hi>
                  </note>, Omnipotency<note n="†" place="margin">Te<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potens Neptune invoco. <hi>Cic. Tuſc. l. 4.</hi>
                  </note>, Creation<note n="‖" place="margin">Ovid. Met. l. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:44571:48"/> Heaven and Earth, Divine Providence<note n="*" place="margin">Jovis nutu &amp; arbitrio coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, terra, maria<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> reguntur. <hi>Cic. de Fin.</hi>
                  </note>, and the like. But it never came into the mind of any Idolater to think his God to be three in one; therefore let us not furniſh our heads only with Speculations, but laying up Divine things within our hearts, and drawing them out into our lives in order to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, that we worſhip one God in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and Trinity in Unity; neither confounding the Perſons, nor dividing the Subſtance, as it is in the Creed of S. <hi>Athanaſius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Deity is the ground of our Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; and as it is neceſſary for every one to be eſtabliſhed in this truth, that there is a God, ſo likewiſe that there is but<note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitas Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis Perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum pluralitate multiplex. <hi>S. Auguſt.</hi>
                  </note> one God, and not a plurality, as the blind idolatrous Heathen imagine. We ought then to make God the object of our higheſt admiration, and of our greateſt love, to offer Sacrifices of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Praiſes to him, in all our ways to acknowledge him, and chearfully do what he commands; to truſt in him, and depend upon him: for our life is lent us for no other end but to be mindful of Eternity, and caſt up our eyes to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, our future happineſs. <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> being askt wherefore man was made? re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:44571:48"/> 
                  <hi>To behold the Heavens.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 8.3.</note> For not a Star ſparkles there, but is a Preacher and Herald to the Majeſty of its Maker. <hi>Empedocles</hi> likewiſe being demanded why he deſired to live in this world? anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, only <hi>to contemplate Heaven.</hi> Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is a kind of religious Aſtronomy, the contemplation and ſtudy of Heaven. No Geometry or meaſuring the Earth in the Chriſtian Mathematicks, unleſs it be that our Souls might more eaſily take footing in Heaven. And as Philoſophy deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing Lines drawn from the Center of the Earth, may go to the Circumference of the Heavens; ſo, according to our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment in theſe ſhort moments, (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are compriz'd the Lines of Life, which we are to live on Earth) ſhall be the definitive Sentence of an Eternal abode. Our true happineſs depends upon our well management of our time here; and it highly concerns us to foreſee what will be our future ſtate: For in this life we ſow thoſe ſeeds, whoſe fruits either of miſery or happineſs, we ſhall gather in another World, and reap them in Eternity.</p>
               <p>Let the ſerious conſideration how ſhort our time is on Earth, enforce up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us a care of redeeming it, and uſe it not to the maintenance of wickedneſs
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:44571:49"/> and vice, but the promotion of true Religion and Vertue; that our future ſtate may be as happy, as it is ſure to be laſting. There are but few that conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that their time here on Earth, is but a Prologue to an everlaſting ſtate. In this vaſt Eternity you muſt live; why do you not let your thoughts be more upon it? Your minds that love to count the days of this narrow life, extend themſelves unto Eternity, where there are no limits at all. Tell the torments of everlaſting Fire, the aking thoughts (if you can) of a burning Soul, that fryes in the Wrath of <hi>God</hi> to eternal Ages: Then number the Joys of Heaven, tell the Notes of that Celeſtial Quire, the Hymns of Praiſes that they ſung; and though thou hadſt a head as big as <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chimedes,</hi> that could tell how many Atoms of duſt were in the Globe of the whole Earth; yet all theſe were but as a ſingle Atom, in compariſon of thoſe endleſs joys or ſorrows. And it is an Oracle of infallible truth, and a promiſe that remains for ever to the righteous; <hi>Your joy ſhall remain,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 16.22.</note> 
                  <hi>none ſhall take it from you.</hi> Therefore Heaven is the moſt lovely, amiable and moſt deſirable ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. The Enjoyments of Riches, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Kingdoms, Feaſtings with us in
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:44571:49"/> this World, are but ſhort and tranſitory; but in Heaven there ſhall be an eternal Feaſt: The Jubilation of the Lamb ſhall be for ever, and ſhall be extended to the vaſt duration of Eternity: O my Soul, why doſt thou not aſpire, and mount up to the Center and Light of Glory, to the Fountain of Beams and Brightneſs, from whence thou waſt derived? How happy ſhalt thou be, when thou ſhalt lay down corruptible rags of Earth, and being delivered out of the Priſon of this wretched Body, may'ſt be thought wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to hear the ſacred Songs of that Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial Harmony, and the Praiſes of the King Eternal of that glorious Empire? How accompliſhed ſhall thy Honour and Glory be, when it ſhall come to thy turn to ſing a gracious Hallelujah? Join unto all this the pleaſure there is to live in the company of Angels; to enjoy the grateful converſation of all thoſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and ſublime Spirits, where Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Troops make raviſhing Muſick; and to behold Armies of Saints, more bright than the Stars of Heaven; to contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate the Sanctity of the Patriarchs, the Hope of the Prophets, the Crown of Martyrs, the white and flowery Garland of Virgins. And as for the Soveraign King, who keeps his Reſidence in the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:44571:50"/> midſt of that glorious People, what tongue is able to ſpeak his praiſe, O <hi>Iſrael!</hi> Now how goodly are thy Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles, how delightful thy Pavilions! Gardens water'd with floods and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains are not ſo flouriſhing, nor are the fruitful Valleys ſo abundant. Let us not then ſuffer our ſelves to be abuſed any longer with the deluſive appearance of this World, but fix our Eye on Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, becauſe it is a fairer object than Earth for our contemplation; joining with the Royal Prophet, as it is in the Verge of the Text, <hi>Whom have I in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven but thee?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All the Bleſſings that we do enjoy, are the ſweet influences of Heaven upon us, <hi>Spiritual</hi> or <hi>Temporal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Spiritual Bleſſings in heavenly places,</hi> ariſe from no other Spring, and are Irradiations of the Trinity, and the great kindneſs of Heaven to Mankind, in relation to theſe Souls of ours. The Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt have all done their parts for them: The Father gave his only Son, the Son gave himſelf, left his Glory, and endured the bitter Death of the Croſs, meerly to keep our Souls from periſhing. The Holy Ghoſt is become (as it were) our Attendant, waits upon us with continual offers of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:44571:50"/> his Grace, to enable us to do that which may preſerve them. Theſe things all the Perſons work equally and inſeparably in reſpect of the Cauſe and Effect. It is a Rule in Divinity, That all the Works of the Trinity <hi>ad extra,</hi> are common to the whole Trinity, God the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt do co-operate and work together, for what one doth, all do; yet in congruity we attribute a diſtinct Act in regard of the Order and Object.</p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <label>(1.) The Father Creates, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.1.</label>
                     <item>In Order the original of <hi>Action</hi> is aſcribed to the Father, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.17, 19.</item>
                     <label>(2.) The Son Redeems, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13.</label>
                     <item>The Nature and Manner of Working, to the Son, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.</item>
                     <label>(3.) The Holy Ghoſt Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminates, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21.</label>
                     <item>The Efficacy and Power to the Holy Ghoſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.12.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The Father is to be adored, as altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Himſelf.</p>
               <p>The Son to be glorified, as that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantial Word.</p>
               <p>The Holy Ghoſt to be magnified, as that Co-eſſential Spirit, eternally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from Both.</p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:44571:51"/>
               <p>The Three Perſons in the Trinity is the Object of our Faith, and we daily owne it in our Creed.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>(1.) <hi>We believe in</hi> God <hi>the Father, who made the World.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>(2.) <hi>In</hi> God <hi>the Son, who redeem'd all Mankind.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>(3.) <hi>In</hi> God <hi>the Holy Ghoſt, who ſanctifies all the Elect People of</hi> God.</item>
               </list>
               <p>An Unity of Eſſence, and a Trinity of Order; <hi>Ordo Originis,</hi> though not <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giminis; Co-ordinativus,</hi> though not <hi>Sub-ordinativus;</hi> of Priority, though not Superiority; a Firſt, a Second, and a Third, though not a higher, lower, and loweſt;<note place="margin">Deut. 6.4. 1 Cor. 8.6.</note> for <hi>the Lord our</hi> God <hi>is one Lord;</hi> the Godhead or Eſſence of <hi>God,</hi> is one undivided.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">This Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, was a point of great diſcourſe amongſt the Ancients; it was the great Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple on which <hi>Parmenides</hi> founded his divine Idea's, delivered by <hi>Plato: Platonicae ideae ortum habuerunt ex Parmenide, cujus magnum principium fuit</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, one and many: one in the Architype Idea God, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in their individual Natures; or otherwiſe it relates to the Unity of the Divine Eſſence, and the Plurality of Perſons; for the Platoniſts ſpeak much of <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a Trinity.</note>
                  <hi>Parmenides</hi> (who followed <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras</hi>) is brought in by <hi>Plato,</hi> philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phizing
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:44571:51"/> on that old Axiom, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, One and Many; and determined thus, That <hi>God</hi> was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> one Divine Eſſence; he was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, one immutable Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; he was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, one Eternal Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. This <hi>Plato</hi> diſcourſeth in his <hi>Phile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> at large, ſhewing how <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, One, was Many, and Many, One. And it is not only good Philoſophy, but ſound Divinity, the Godhead conſidered diverſly; for the manner of Being, is Three Perſons in One Eſſence; the <hi>Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 1 Joh. 5.7.</p>
               <p>The Father is the Firſt Perſon of the Trinity, having Foundation in none, of Perſonal Subſtance.</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Not begotten to the Father.</p>
               <p>The Son is the Second Perſon of the Trinity, having Foundation of Perſonal Subſtance, of whom he is eternally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.26.</p>
               <p n="2">(2.) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Begotten to the Son.</p>
               <p>The Holy Ghoſt is the Third Perſon in the Trinity, having Foundation from the Father and the Son; from both which he eſpecially proceedeth, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.26.</p>
               <p n="3">(3.) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Proceeding to the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:44571:52"/>
               <p>Here is a threefold Unity of Perſons in one Nature, of Natures in One Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, of Natures and Perſons in One Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>In the Firſt is one <hi>God.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>In the Second one <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>In the Third one <hi>Spirit.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>All this Unity is but to uſher in a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Deity. S. <hi>Paul</hi> concludes all with an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>There is one God,</hi> Eph. 4.6.</p>
               <p>And the Soul carrieth an Image of the Unity of the Godhead, and Trinity of Perſons, in that there is one Soul with three Faculties, of Underſtanding, Will, and Memory. Let us all now lift up our heart and voice, and praiſe <hi>God,</hi> chant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth the Anthem of the Seraphims, for the Redemption of the World by our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the Second Perſon of the Trinity; concluding with S. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil</hi>'s Liturgy, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>O God our God, who haſt ſent this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Bread, the Food of all the World,</hi> Our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to be to us a Saviour, a Redeemer. Therefore with Angels and Archangels, and all the Company of Heaven, we laud and magnifie thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Name, evermore praiſing thee, and ſaying, <hi>Holy, holy, holy, Lord God of Hoſts, Heaven and Earth are full of thy Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:44571:52"/>
               <p>Secondly, As <hi>Spiritual,</hi> ſo <hi>Temporal</hi> Bleſſings are the product of Heaven. This Day is a ſignal Inſtance, and carries with it the Pomp of Blaze and Splendour, as it is the Anniverſary of His Majeſty's hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Birth and Nativity. And that Divine Providence that brought him this Day into the World, hath led him by the hand of his viſible goodneſs. Ever ſince he entred the porch of life, and walked upon the pavement of the Earth, he has had the Royal Charter of Heaven, and enjoy'd the teſtimony of Gods ſpecial care, even a Writ of Protection;<note place="margin">1 Chron. 16.22.</note> 
                  <hi>Touch not mine Anointed, do my Prophets no harm.</hi> His Life hath been a continued Series of Divine Favour. The Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary hath not been able to do him vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; the Son of wickedneſs could not hurt him: but he hath ſmitten down his Foes before his face, cloathed them with ſhame, and wounded them that hated him. The great Majeſty of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven was a Helmet of Salvation unto him, a ſtrong Tower of Defence againſt his cruel Enemies, Domeſtick and Foreign, at <hi>home</hi> and <hi>abroad.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Cruel Enemies at <hi>home,</hi> who inveſted their Sword with the Authority of Law, and made themſelves after the Image of a King, and uſurp'd the Seat
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:44571:53"/> Royal, chang'd the Kingdom into a State, and Monarchy into a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. This was in the time of our late Troubles and Confuſions, when Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy was ſhaken off, Religion and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty were loſt, and Laws and Liberty were with no ſmall violence invaded, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as in the days of <hi>Jeroboam</hi>) whoever would,<note place="margin">1 Kings 13.33.</note> were conſecrated Prieſts of the high places. And when Souldiers turn'd Preachers, every act of Providence that ſeems to favour their Deſigns, ſhall be the voice of God: Every opportunity to do miſchief to ſuch as they oppoſe, ſhall be interpreted a Command from Heaven to do it.<note place="margin">Judg. 5.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Curſe ye Meroz</hi> was the Text, Rapine and Plunder the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the Uſe. Wars ſounded as loud from the Pulpit as the Drum, as if it had been the task of the Heavens to kill and ſlay, and for its Arms hung in the Zodiack Man's Anatomy, to ſhew they were born with thoſe that aroſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Dragon's Teeth in the Poet, <hi>Mutuis perire gladiis,</hi> to bleed to death on one another's Swords. And here I may lead your thoughts to the unnatural Civil War in our <hi>Britiſh</hi> Iſle, when Tribe did riſe againſt Tribe, Brother againſt Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<q>
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:44571:53"/>Marte cadunt ſubito per mutua vulnera fratres.<note place="margin">Ovid.</note>
                  </q> And the ſight of one <hi>Aceldama,</hi> one field of Blood will raiſe mens careleſs thoughts to a due valuation and grateful appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of the comforts we enjoy under our moſt Gracious Soveraign. He that has eſcaped with him, in <hi>Job,</hi> to bring news of rapine and violence, can beſt tell us what it is to ſee a flouriſhing Land become a Sea of Blood; becauſe War playes <hi>Pliny</hi>'s Cockatrice, annoying whatſoever it doth touch. He can tell us what it is to ſee the Horſe in equal ſtate with its Rider, both of them wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering in their own gore. He can ſhew us what it is to ſee the obedient Son run over his ſlain Father to eſcape the hands of his own Executioner. He can ſhew us what it is to ſee the burning of Cities, and the woful Inhabitants martyr'd in the flames. Is not every Siege the Funeral of a City?<note n="*" place="margin">Quot obſidia, tot urbium funera; quot pugnae, tot homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num lanienae; quot agmina, tot ruris ſupplicia; quot turmae &amp; catervae, cohortes &amp; acies, tot ſuriae ad exitium agrorum &amp; hominum armatae. <hi>Putean. in ſtat. bell. &amp; pacis lit.</hi>
                  </note> eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pitched Battle a Maſſacre? If a <hi>Samuel,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.33. hew <hi>Agag</hi> in pieces: a <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> in the heat of War, falls a cutting <hi>Ammonites,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.3. Sin, Satan, and War have all one Name, Evil is the beſt of
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:44571:54"/> them. The beſt of Sin is deformity, the beſt of Satan enmity, the beſt of War miſery<note n="*" place="margin">The Turkiſh Hiſtory makes mention of the Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian <hi>Tam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rlane,</hi> when he walked amongſt the ſlain a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a bloody Victory againſt the <hi>Muſcovites;</hi> He account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thoſe Princes unhappy, which by the deſtruction of their own kind, ſought to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance their own honour, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting himſelf grieved, even from his heart, to ſee ſuch ſorrowful tokens of his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory.</note>. It is no wonder now to complain (as the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator to the <hi>Athenians</hi>) what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they gain in their thrifty Peace, they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of by thoſe conſuming Tumults; for what Paradiſe is there under Heaven, which a laſting War will not eaſily turn into a Wilderneſs? Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in this N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion have wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed the truth of it with their eyes, and its horrour with their tears: by theſe inconveniences we may judge of the benefits of Peace, and may ſee what gracious opportunities it doth yield for the practice of Religion and Godlineſs. We may behold with joy and thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that the Ark, the Teſtimony of Gods preſence, which was long held ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptive among the <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> is now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned and happily ſetled among us; and that his Worſhip is duly performed in his Word and Sacraments. Let his lungs waſte in his breaſt, let his ſpirits decay, let his tongue languiſh to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual ſilence, that will not beſeech God to eſtabliſh this bleſſing as firm as the days of Heaven, and wiſh its continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:44571:54"/> O then pray for the Peace<note n="*" place="margin">Pulchriùs vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer quàm enſis ſplendet, bidens quàm haſta; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liùs ferro ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacta agrorum, quàm agmina agricolarum proſcinduntur, <hi>ſaith</hi> Puteanus.</note> of our <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that love her; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, for the life and proſperity of the Monarch of Great <hi>Britain,</hi> King <hi>Charles</hi> II. our dread Soveraign, <hi>the light of our eyes, and the breath of our noſtrils, Lam.</hi> 4.20. who cauſes malignant va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours to vaniſh, and diſpels thoſe clouds of miſchief by his Princely power that would turn Religion into Rebellion, and Faith into Faction, cry up Priviledge to invade Regal Prerogative, and under the notion of the Preſervers of our Peace, and Defenders of our Liberties, reach out their hand to turn the ſtream of Royalty, and ſubvert an excellent Monarchy into a Tyrannical Republick. The Fallacy having been put on the Kingdom, and Cheat acted once before, it will not eaſily prevail with men of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and rational judgments, to renounce their Religion (the beſt in the world) or their Loyalty and obedience to the beſt of Kings, whoſe Princely Goodneſs is not more tender of the Imperial Crown and Dignity, than of the Peace and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity of the Subject. The one as it regards Royal honour, the other the care of his People, to cauſe Religion happily to flouriſh, and Liberty, Laws and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty to be ſafe and inviolable, (with
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:44571:55"/> the Bleſſings of Heaven) notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſubtile inſinuations and cunning ſtratagems of the old Enemies of Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy and the Church, to throw us back into a relapſe; which reminds us of the late Rebellion, when men in Buff durſt proclaim themſelves the only Legal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Nation: and theſe, like a mighty Torrent, did drive all before them, with an unruly violence, brake down the banks of Eccleſiaſtical Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, making no difference betwixt things Sacred and Common, ſwallowed up Churches with their Revenues, and laid deſolate Sanctuaries of Piety and Religion. Here we may wail out an <hi>Epicedium,</hi> War and deſolation, poverty and paleneſs, and garments roll'd in blood, hearing the woful groans of dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men, and bitter lamentations of Children for their Parents. The Orphan blubbers his cheeks, and ſighs with <hi>Eliſha, O my Father, my Father.</hi> Now <hi>David</hi> breaths out an Elegy, and, <hi>O Abſalom, Abſalom! my Son, my Son!</hi> And <hi>Rachel</hi> likewiſe <hi>weeps, and will not be comforted, becauſe they are not.</hi> Theſe were the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries this Kingdom groan'd under, after the Barbarous and horrid Murder of that Glorious Martyr King <hi>Charles the Firſt,</hi> of ever Bleſſed Memory. And ſo it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:44571:55"/> under the heavy yoke of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent Uſurpation, till his Majeſty's hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Reſtauration, actual Government, and gracious Reign over us in peace and quietneſs, ſecurity and freedom. We owe the happineſs of theſe temporal en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments, (under God) to the prudent Conduct of Regal Majeſty. And here take this Theſis or Doctrine by way of affirmative Poſition.</p>
               <p>If the Church be depriv'd of Kingly Majeſty, ſhe is as apt to be infected with home-bred Errours as Foreign injuries; for when there was no King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Judg. 17.6.</note> every man did what was right in his own eyes. We ſee then the Office of a King is attended with as much burden as Juriſdiction. He muſt encounter with Adverſaries. For has the holy Oyl been pour'd upon his Head, and the Crown ſetled upon it by Divine Providence, which over-rules Nature? He that has given him the Crown, gave the Sword alſo to ſecure and guard it: and as it was <hi>Judah</hi>'s Prerogative to ſway the Royal Scepter, ſo alſo to yield Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for the King is <hi>Cuſtos utriuſque Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>búlae, Defender of the Faith,</hi> and a <hi>Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Father to the Church.</hi> And the Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Power, and Soveraign Authority (with God's Bleſſing) may ſtill preſerve
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:44571:56"/> the true and ancient Conſtitution both of Church and State from Anarchy and Diſorder, from Popiſh Superſtition and Fanatical Faction. For the King has his Authority over us from Heaven, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the Lord ſets up Kings,</hi> ſaith the Father: And, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Kings are from God,</hi> ſays the Heathen. Therefore I muſt be ſubject, purely out of Conſcience, for the Lord's ſake. The Religion of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (like the Laws of <hi>Draco</hi>) are written in Blood, and advanced by Policy, and propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Violence: their Vow of Pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is ſuch, as to covet Kingdoms, their Humility is ſuch, that they tread upon the necks of Emperours, their Charity is ſuch, as to kill Kings, making black TREASON a glorious Act, and to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit the brighteſt Crown of Immortality, and higheſt Seat in Heaven. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Chriſtianity never uſed the Sword (the Kingdom of Heaven is another kind of <hi>Warfare</hi>) Chriſtianity came attired in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World with the white of meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.4.</note> humility and patience. Chriſt, the Prince of Peace, never pull'd the Crown from any Prince's head, but commands the payment of all Duties to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and acknowledgeth <hi>Pilate</hi>'s power to be from above. Nay, when our bleſſed Lord
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:44571:56"/> had power with his <hi>Ego ſum</hi> to ſtrike all his Adverſaries to the ground, or cauſed <hi>Legions of Angels</hi> to have ſtood in his juſt defence to revenge the injury of the <hi>People,</hi> the violence of the <hi>Souldiers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 26.53.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 19.15. Mat. 27.27, 28, 29. Luke 23.11. Mark 15 15.</note> the ſcorn of <hi>Herod,</hi> the judgment of <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> yet he yielded himſelf patiently to ſuffer; to teach all his Diſciples, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance is an affront to Divine Authority. This was the Spirit of the great Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar of our Religion; this was the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius of his Doctrine and his practice. Nor did any of his Followers ever rebel againſt their Prince, uſurp the State, or diſturb the Government; and though it was their unhappy Fate at firſt to be accuſed as Factious and Seditious, yet none were better Subjects, nor teſtified their Allegiance more to Authority. S. <hi>Paul</hi> in the days of Heathen Perſecution and Tyranny lays down this Hypotheſis, <hi>There is no Power but of God: the Powers that be,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>are ordained of God.</hi> If Religion be pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, an Heathen muſt not be reſiſted. If Tyranny, 'tis damnation to oppoſe a <hi>Nero. They that reſiſt, ſhall receive,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 13.1, 2.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the wrath and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. This made the Primitive Chriſtians, thoſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Spirits, where they could not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:44571:57"/> to ſuffer, and thought it the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt piece of devotion to be patient under all oppoſitions. They were ſo far from conſpiring into tumultuous Combinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that they freely offered themſelves to the fury of their Enemies, and quietly ſuffered all extremities of death and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, chuſing rather to be crown'd Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs for Religion, than be puniſhed as Traitors for Rebellion. It was not diſability<note n="*" place="margin">—Si hoſtes exertos agere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>llemus, non deeſſet nobis vis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>merorum &amp; copiarum: Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra omnia implevimus, urbes, inſulas, caſtella, municipia, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliabula, caſtra ipſa, tribus, decurias, palatium, ſenatum, ſorum. Cui bello idonei non prom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ti ſuiſſemus. etiam impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res copiis, qui tam libenter tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidamur? Si non apud iſtam diſciplinam magis occidiliceret quàm occidere. <hi>Tertul.</hi>
                  </note>, but du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, not want of money, or Martial proweſs, but a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend regard to Imperial Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, as commanded by God, cauſed them not to avenge themſelves. The ancient Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs in ſaddeſt days (as <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> tells us in his Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getical Defence of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans) had courage to ſay to their greateſt Adverſaries, <hi>Cruciate, torquete, damnate, atterite, probatio eſt innocentiae noſtrae iniquitas veſtra;</hi> Rack us, torture us, do with us what you will, or what you can, your iniquity is but the proof of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, you think to weary out the Saints of the <hi>moſt High,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 7.25.</note> by inventing of greater torments; but the Sect<note n="‖" place="margin">Exquiſitior quaeque crude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litas, veſtra illecebra eſt, magis ſectae noſtrae plures efficimur quoties mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur. <hi>Tertul. Apol.</hi>
                  </note> of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:44571:57"/> is the ſtrangeſt Sect that you ever read of, it is allured by thoſe miſeries whereby others are terrified.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> writing to <hi>Demetrianus,</hi> the Governour of <hi>Africa,</hi> and Chriſtian Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutor. <hi>God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is the revenger of his Servants, when they are annoyed; therefore none of us reſiſts, nor avengeth</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Nemo noſtrûm quando appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henditur, nec ſe adverſus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juriam veſtram, quamvis nimius copioſus ſit no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter populus, ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcitur— Odiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe non licet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis, &amp; ſic Deo placemus, dum nullam pro injuria vicem reddimus. <hi>S. Cypr. ad Demetr.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>himſelf of your unjuſt violence, though our people are numerous and able to do it.</hi> The innocent reſt content with their undeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved puniſhments and tortures; and thus we pleaſe God the more, whilſt we reta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liate no injury.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="‖" place="margin">Euſeh. Eccleſ. Hiſt. l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> tells us, That in the <hi>Diocle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> Perſecution in <hi>Thebais,</hi> which was none of the greateſt Countries of <hi>Africa,</hi> were ſlain, by various methods of cruel death, ſo many, that the Executioners were tired out.</p>
               <p>In the time of <hi>Trajan</hi> alſo, <hi>Tiberius</hi> the Preſident of <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> gives this relation in his Letter to the Emperor: <hi>I am wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with puniſhing and deſtroying the Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilaeans, who are called Chriſtians, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your Majeſties Command.</hi> It was the inſpired patience and courage of theſe great<note n="†" place="margin">The World admires the <hi>Lacedaemonians</hi> and <hi>Romans,</hi> and they that had courage in any Age or place to dye for their Country, they were ſo eſteem'd by the Heathens, that they had Statues erected, Pictures ingraven, Titles of Honour inſcribed; the World doing what it could to make their Names immortal, how much better to ſuffer for Chriſt? What Soul would not deſire to have his Name inrolled in that Catalogue among the Cloud of Witneſſes, who wander'd up and down, deſtitute, afflicted, tormented, were ſtoned, ſlain with the Sword, ſawn aſunder, yet not accepting deliverance on unworthy terms, becauſe they looked for a better reſurrection, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.35, 37.</note> Heroes that blunted the very
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:44571:58"/> edge of Perſecution, to tire as the hands, ſo the wits of their Tormentors, to turn their pity at their ſuffering into envy at their patience, to hug their Stakes as ſo many horns of the Altar, letting fall<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <p>Magni animi eſt injurias de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicere. <hi>Sen. de Ira, l. 2. c. 32.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Abſit itaque à ſervo Chriſti ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le inquinamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, ut patien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia majoribus tentationibus praeparata, in frivolis exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat. <hi>Tertul. de bon. pat.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> not ſo much as a tear, leſt it might quench ſome ſparkle of that fire wherein they were (with <hi>Elijah</hi>) to ride to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as in a Chariot; <hi>ignis igni remedium,</hi> 'twas this fire of holy Zeal and Chriſtian Loyalty or Charity which out-burn'd that of Malice and Envy. And in the midſt of the fierceſt flames that Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm and Cruelty could invent, paid the Tribute of a peaceable ſubjection to their Murderers, and made unforced acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments of the Right they had to their obedience. And the Church of <hi>England</hi> teaches no other Doctrine than what was taught by the Prophets and Apoſtles themſelves, <hi>i. e.</hi> Obedience and Submiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Kings and Governours. In the Prophecy of <hi>Obadiah</hi> they are called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Saviours</hi> or <hi>Deliverers.</hi> In <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel</hi>'s
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:44571:58"/> language they are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds,</hi> to feed and rule the People. In S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s they are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>God's Miniſters;</hi> nay <hi>Elohim,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 22.28.</note> 
                  <hi>Gods</hi> by Office and Deputation, to govern the affairs of men on Earth. The Apoſtles alſo char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged thoſe whom they employ'd in ſetling of the Churches, to <hi>put them in mind to be ſubject to Principalities and Powers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 3.1.</note> 
                  <hi>and to obey Magiſtrates.</hi> And S. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation is, <hi>Submit your ſelves to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.13.</note> not only unto the King <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>as ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme,</hi> but <hi>unto Governours</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>as being ſent by him. Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion</hi> then <hi>is as the ſin of Witchcraft, and Diſobedience as the iniquity of Idolatry.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.23.</note> For whoſoever diſobeys the Viceroy, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts the Soveraign; they fight againſt God, and attempt to croſs the Decrees of Heaven, and fruſtrate the Counſel of the moſt High, who ſays,<note place="margin">Prov. 8.15.</note> 
                  <hi>By me Kings reign.</hi> And it is the aſſertion of <hi>Plato,</hi> That a Kingdom is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a Divine Good,</hi> which imprints on our minds a double inſtruction, to <hi>Fear God, and Honour the King,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17. Firſt, to adorn the Chriſtian Religion with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and piety of life. It is Religion that ennobles man, erects his affections, and eſtates him in a happineſs above Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:44571:59"/> alters his very being, and puts him in oppoſition to what he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Religion is the moſt effectual in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to reform mens lives, and bring them into an hatred of their vices, which all Moraliſts, eſpecially the <hi>Pythagoreans,</hi> after all their induſtry, deſpaired of. What Reports <hi>Diogenes Laertius,</hi> and <hi>Valerius Maximus</hi> make of <hi>Polemus,</hi> the Convert of <hi>Zeno,</hi> are but mean and low things, if compared with the Acts and glorious Succeſs of Chriſtianity; whoſe virtue and influence upon mens Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, inables them to ſubdue Self, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come their Vices, check the impetuous force of their Paſſions, and withſtand their own carnal and ſenſual Inclinations, the greateſt and moſt noble Conqueſt.</p>
               <p>As the Luſtre of Chriſtianity was thus bright and glorious in the Primitive Conſtitution; ſo was the honour of its Profeſſors, that they were of ſuch piety and integrity, that their Adverſaries confeſſed, that their Religion was their only ruine.</p>
               <p>Let us therefore be ſo ſtedfaſt in our Religion, unſhaken in our Faith, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in our Devotion, and holy and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted in our Lives, that <hi>Wiſdom may be juſtified</hi> not only <hi>of her Children,</hi> but Enemies alſo: which lays the greateſt
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:44571:59"/> obligation on us to live the moſt holy and religious life towards <hi>God:</hi> For were we more holy and righteous in our ways, and did we walk in newneſs of life, we ſhould more convince the World of the Truth of our Religion.<note place="margin">Pſal. 93.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Holineſs</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>becomes</hi> (O Lord) <hi>thine houſe for ever.</hi> No garment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the Church ſo well, as the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Holineſs. It is Sanctity that is the Churches Glory: It is the Ephod of Purity that is the Churches Excellency. Our firſt Creation ſet before us, as Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roglyphicks before the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> whoſe very Shapes and Figures were Doctrinal; and by a kind of Oratory, preach'd the Spectators Duty. What elſe means the Image of <hi>God</hi> in the Soul, but that it might continually act and work accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Pattern, <hi>viz.</hi> Godlineſs, after whoſe Likeneſs it was created according to Holineſs and Perfection, which it brought down from Heaven; that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting ſtill upon the ſame Image, it might <hi>be holy as he is holy.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.15.</note> For a holy life and Chriſtian works, are the very way to the glorious Viſion, and Fruition of the great <hi>God</hi> in an everlaſting bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Life: Therefore, <hi>Fear God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 6.22.</note> 
                  <hi>and honour the King,</hi> which is the beſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian practice, and brings me to the next
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:44571:60"/> gradation in our Diſcourſe, <hi>viz.</hi> to crown our Zeal with Loyalty to the King; for he is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, wears Gods Image, and beautifies the World<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Plut. ad Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect indoct. Dei enim imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem habet Rex, ſicut Chriſti Epiſcopus. <hi>S. Aug. Vet. Teſt. quaeſt. 35.</hi>
                  </note> with Order and Government, whereby ſo many millions of men do breathe the life of peace and comfort. For ſooner might a heap of Ants be brought to an uniformity in motion, and thoſe little bodies that play up and down the Air in a careleſs poſture, to a regularity, than the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or popular ſort, if they were not held in by the reins of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; whither would the fury of mens paſſions lead them? if they were not bounded with Authority, if the rapacity of theſe Orbs were not ſlack'd by the courſe of the higher Spheres, and ſubdu'd to an awful ſubjection; Religion would quickly feel a heavy Deſtiny, and the World be drown'd in blood, as it was once in water. The Sword of Authority is put into the hand of the King by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God. To the like ſenſe alſo is that of <hi>Neſtor</hi> to <hi>Agamemnon:</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>—</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:44571:60"/> 
                  <hi>Jove</hi> lent thee thy Scepter and Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. On this account ſpeaks <hi>Themi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtius,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, God ſent Regal Power from Heaven. Holy <hi>Athanaſius</hi> alſo confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Power of Kings to be of God, and their impiety not to be puniſh'd by man:<note place="margin">Ad Antioch. quaeſt. <hi>55.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Sicut in toto mundo Deus Rex eſt Imperator, &amp; poteſtatem exercet in omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus:</hi> As God is King and Emperour o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all the World, and exerciſeth his Power in all Creatures: ſo the King and Prince is over all earthly men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Lord,</hi> ſaith <hi>Athanaſius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Athanaſ. apud Epiphan. Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ. <hi>68.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>to</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine, <hi>judge between thee and me, ſince thou giveſt way to my falſe accuſers against me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let us ſend our prayers and tears,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Cyprian</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Mittamus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s &amp; lachrymas cordis ad Deum legatos. <hi>S. Cypr. lib. 4. Epiſt. 4.</hi>
                  </note> to the perſecuted Chriſtians, <hi>as Meſſengers and Ambaſſadours of our hearts unto God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſpeaking of Obedience to Princes, ſays, They are to be defended not by killing, but by dying, not by cruelty, but by patience.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> lived under five Emperours, <hi>Conſtantius, Julianus, Valens, Valentinianus,</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius:</hi> in all which time he could find no remedy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Tyranny, Hereſie, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie of Princes, beſides prayers and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:44571:61"/> tears, ſpeaking of <hi>Julian</hi>'s<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; Greg. Nazian. in Julian. Orat. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> time, we had no other wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, nor wall, nor bulwark, but our hope in God left us: whom could we have either to hear our prayers, or to protect our perſons, but him?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. <hi>124.</hi>
                  </note>And S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, That though <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> was an Apoſtate, an Idolater, and a wicked man, the Chriſtians were ſubject to him, their <hi>Temporal</hi> Lord, out of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to their <hi>Eternal</hi> Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Rogamus, Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte, non pugna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus: non time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ſed roga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. <hi>S. Ambr. l. 5. ep. 33.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>We intreat, O Emperour,</hi> (ſay the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers in <hi>Ambroſe</hi> his Cauſe againſt the <hi>Arians) we fight not; neither fear we, and yet we intreat only.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We will ſtand to it, and fight it out, even to death,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Stahimus, &amp; pugnabimus uſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ad mortem, ſi ita oportuerit, pro matre no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra, non ſcutis &amp; gladiis, ſed precibus fleti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ad Deum. <hi>S. Bern. Epiſt. 221.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>if need be,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard, for our Mother the Church; but with ſuch weapons as we may, not with Sword and Target, but with tears and prayers to God.</hi> Theſe were the weapons of the old Chriſtian Martyrs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> alſo to <hi>Scapula</hi> the Viceroy of <hi>Carthage, Abſit ut ultionem nos aliquam machinemur, quam à Deo expectamus:</hi> Far be it for us to attempt or plot any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge of our wrongs, which we expect from God. <hi>We</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are defamed for ſeditious againſt Imperial Majeſty</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">—Circa Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtatem Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris infamamur, tamen nunquam Albiniani, nec Nigriani, nec Caſſiani inveniri potuerunt Chriſtiani.— Chriſtianus nullius eſt hoſlis, nedum Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratoris, quem ſciens à Deo ſuo conſtitui, neceſſe eſt ut &amp; ipſum diligat, &amp; revereatur, &amp; honoret, &amp; ſalvum velit, cum toto Romano Imperio quouſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſeculum ſtabit.— Colimus ergo &amp; Imperatorem ſic, quomodo &amp; nobis li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet, &amp; ipſi expedit, ut hominem à Deo ſecundum, &amp; quicquid eſt à Deo conſtitutum, &amp; ſolo Deo minorem. <hi>Tertul. ad Scap.</hi>
                  </note>,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:44571:61"/> 
                  <hi>and yet never were the Chriſtians Rebels, as ſeveral of your own Religion have been,</hi> Albinus, Niger, Caſſius <hi>were Traitors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst</hi> Marcus Antonius, Commodus, Pertinax, <hi>and</hi> Severus <hi>the Emperours.</hi> A Chriſtian is Enemy to no man, much leſs the Emperours, knowing that Regal Dignity is conſtituted and ordained of God, and therefore neceſſarily to be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, reverenced, and honoured, whoſe proſperity, together with the welfare of all the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, we wiſh and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire ſo long as the World ſhall endure. We honour and worſhip the Emperour, ſo as it is lawful for us, and expedient for him, as a mortal man, next unto God, of whom he holds all his Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, only ſubject to God, and ſo we make him Soveraign over all. And it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, we live according to the Diſcipline of Divine patience, whilſt being ſo great a multitude, we behave our ſelves with peace and ſubmiſſion. This hath been the practice of good Chriſtians in all Ages, and to do otherwiſe, is to ſit in the Throne of the Almighty, and to
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:44571:62"/> ſlight the Legiſlative Power, turning God out of his Soveraignty, affronting him in his Authority and in his Laws, making themſelves the ſure Heirs of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, becauſe the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>They that reſiſt ſhall receive damnation.</hi> All Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, Prelates, Peers, and People are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden with the tongue to <hi>revile Kings,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 22.28.</note> with the heart to <hi>think ill of them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10.20</note> or with the hand to <hi>reſiſt them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 13.2.</note> It is not the wickedneſs<note n="*" place="margin">—Si à ſaevo Principe cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deliter torquemur, &amp;c. ſubeat primum delictorum noſtrorum recordatio, quae talibus haud du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bie Domini flagellis caſtigan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: inde humilitas impatien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam noſtram fraenabit, nobis nullum aliud quàm parendi &amp; patiendi datum eſt mandatum. <hi>Calv. Inſtit.</hi>
                  </note> of the Prince ſhould cauſe any to neglect their duty to his Perſon, nor the injuries done by him tempt them to forget their Allegiance; becauſe in the worſt<note n="‖" place="margin">—In homine deterrimo, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nore<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> omni indigniſſimo, penes quem modò ſit publica poteſtas, praeclara illa &amp; divina pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas reſidet, quam Dominus ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiae &amp; judicii ſui miniſtris verbo ſuo detulit: proinde à ſubditis eadem in reverentia &amp; dignitate habendus, quantum ad publicam obedientiam attinet, quâ optimum Regem, ſi daretur, habituri eſſent. <hi>Calv. Inſtit.</hi>
                  </note> and moſt unworthy King the Divine Authority reſides, which God in his Word hath given to righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Magiſtrates; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Subjects are to have the ſame reverence for him (as far as it belongs unto publick obedience) as for the beſt King. The Divine Wiſdom by the Tyranny of cruel Kings<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <p>—Etſi non loquatur Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus, ſatis tamen flagellis ipſis &amp; plagis vocat; ut enim Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pturam nobis omnem, Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, Doctores, &amp; Monitores de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe fingamus, aerumnis tamen &amp; calamitatibus nos erudit, ut breviter definire poſſimus, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gam vocationem ad poenitenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am eſſe. <hi>Calvin.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Wicked Princes by Divine permiſſion are exalted to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the ſins of the people:</hi> tollenda eſt igitur culpa, ut ceſſet Tyrannorum plaga. <hi>Aquin. de Regim. Princ. l. 1. c. 6.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note>, makes tryal of the Vertues and Graces of his Saints and people, that they who are found patient in
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:44571:62"/> tribulation, conſtant in truth, loyal in ſubjection, may be crown'd with glory and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. It was the height of <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s ambition to walk in the ſteps of <hi>Alexander;</hi> and of the Turkiſh Emperour to walk in the ſteps of <hi>Caeſar;</hi> and of <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> to walk in the ſteps of <hi>Miltiades:</hi> ſo it is the height of a Chriſtians glory to be a follower of Chriſt, who is the Mirrour of Angels, and Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Heaven, whoſe life is the perfect Idea of all Vertue, and exact Pattern of holy living; tread therefore in the holy ſteps of the bleſſed Jeſus, the Saviour of Mankind, whoſe actions ſhould be our inſtruction, and the patience and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence practiſed by our Lord, the rule of our imitation;<note place="margin">Leo in Serm. de Nat. Dom.</note> 
                  <hi>Fruſtra appellamur Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiani, ſi imitatores non fuerimus Chriſti.</hi> Chriſt and his Apoſtles, both by Precept and Example, left to all ſucceeding ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations Chriſtian obedience and ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Had the Language of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and ſacred Oracle of the Word, ſo poſitively declared againſt Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as it has REBELLION, the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of this Age would have got into the Revelations to looſen the Seals, pour out the Vials, and phantaſtically interpreted
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:44571:63"/> the Fates of Kingdoms, and Churches ruine. God is angry with them (ſays the elegant Moraliſt <hi>Plutarch</hi>) that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit his Thunder and Lightning, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, his Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter, his Thunderbolt, and his Trident: he will not let them meddle with theſe; he does not love they ſhould imitate him in his abſolute Dominion and Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in the arm of his Power, or finger of his Miracles, but loves to ſee them darting out thoſe amiable and cheriſhing <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, thoſe beamings out of juſtice, goodneſs and clemency, imitating his meekneſs and humility, long-ſuffering and patience, charity and obedience. And as many as lived to Chriſt's ſacred Inſtitution, did never revile the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Tyrants, (but carry themſelves in a demeanour towards them, to obey and be ſubject,<note place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s tanquam Deo, malis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter Deum; tam bonis quam ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, &amp; tanquam Deo, &amp; propter Deum.</note> as one ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Unto good Rulers as God, bad Rulers for God, <hi>Submit your ſelves,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.13. <hi>to every ordinance of man,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>for the Lords ſake, and to the King as ſupreme</hi>) much leſs repelling by force their violence, leſt they ſhould be found <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, fighters againſt God. What preſumption is it then to contradict the Laws of our Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:44571:63"/> and ſhew diſreſpect to that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of men, which God intends as his Vicegerents? The immenſe perfections of a Deity being ſuch, that the frailty of humane Nature can't bear his immediate converſes (let not our Law-giver ſpeak unto us, except we ſhall dye) therefore he rules us by our own Species, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns us by men like our ſelves: But as the dignity and excellency of Angels are above other Creatures, ſo of Magiſtrates above other men. The Heathen Poet calls Kings <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, perſons di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely deſcended. God has imparted to them his own Name, <hi>Ego dixi,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 82.6, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>I have ſaid, Ye are Gods, and Sons of the moſt High,</hi> all of you. As he hath given an eminent appellation unto them, ſo he hath conferred an eminent Authority upon them, a Divine power<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Diotog. de Regno.</note>, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting and reſembling his own Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, and they are Sacred and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, becauſe they bear not the Sword in vain. And the ſame Authority that binds us to obey God, commands us to revere thoſe that ſo ſignally wear his Image. Nothing can more oblige Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, than to oblige thoſe Heaven hath ſet over us, eſpecially our Princes and Governours. Let us therefore ſhew our future Loyalty to the King, and readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:44571:64"/> to obey him, by ſubmitting our ſelves firſt unto God, whoſe MINISTER he is, that theſe things are enjoyned, not ſecular men only, ſaith S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>S. Chryſoſtom. in Rom. Hom. 23.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Et eadem habent etiam Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret. Theophyl. &amp; Oecumen. ad <hi>Rom. 13.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</p>
                  </note>, but even Prieſts and Monks alſo, the Apoſtle evidently demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, when he ſaith, <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the higher Power.</hi> Be thou Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, or Evangeliſt, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, or whatſoever thou beeſt elſe, thou muſt not only obey them, but even be ſubject unto them. Here we may juſtly tax the intolerable Tyranny and Ambition of that <hi>man of ſin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.3.</note> who not only exempts himſelf from all Civil ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, but even<note n="‖" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sic</hi> Alexand. III. Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ric. I. <hi>Imper. pede collum com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſit.</hi> Philip. Bergom. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plem. <hi>Anno</hi> 1160. Petr. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin. <hi>rerum Venet.</hi> lib. 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyr. Maſſon. <hi>in</hi> Alex. 3. <hi>Et</hi> Coeleſtinus Hen. VI. <hi>Imper. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piti coronam pedibus impoſuit, eiſdem<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> denuò dimovit.</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Hoveden. Annal. par. po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. <hi>in</hi> Rich. I. <hi>&amp;</hi> Ranulph. Polychron. l. 1. c. 26.</note> tramples on the Crowns of Princes in a moſt preſumptuous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. <hi>Gregory</hi> VII. feared neither God nor man, when he erected the Papal Croiſier againſt the Regal Scepter, and read the Sentence of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>privation againſt the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Henry;</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Carol. Sig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n. de Regno Ital.</hi> lib. 9. in Vita Hen. III.</note> 
                  <hi>Ego Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Apoſtolica, &amp;c.</hi> I by my Power Apoſtolical do bereave <hi>Henry</hi> of the <hi>German</hi> Kingdom, and do deprive
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:44571:64"/> him of all ſubjection of Chriſtian men, abſolving all men from the Allegiance ſworn unto him. And as I do deject <hi>Henry</hi> from Royal Dignity: ſo I exalt <hi>Rodolph</hi> (Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> that was a ſworn Subject to the Emperour) to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern the Kingdom, granting unto all men, that ſhall ſerve him againſt the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, forgiveneſs of their ſins in this life, and in the life to come. It is no wonder, that <hi>Gregory</hi> his Chair clave aſunder, as ſome Writers<note n="*" place="margin">Benno Card. in Vit. Gregor. VII.</note> affirm, at the giving of the Sentence, becauſe the proud Pope and his wicked Decree were too heavy a burden for S. <hi>Peters</hi> Stool of humility to bear. The ancient Fathers were not acquainted with this Divinity of the Popes Deity, they were utterly ignorant of it. <hi>We worſhip the Emperour,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Colimus Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torem ut homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem à Deo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum, ſolo Deo minorem. <hi>Tertul. ad Sca. pul.</hi>
                  </note> ſaith <hi>Tertullian, as a man that is next to God, inferiour to none but God alone.</hi> The Speech of <hi>Optatus</hi> ſpoken of him by that inſolent Schiſmatick <hi>Donatus,</hi> may be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to the proud Romiſh Prelate, ſince<note n="‖" place="margin">Cùm ſupra Imperatorem non ſit niſi Deus qui fecit Imperato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, dum ſe Donatus ſuper Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratorem extollit, jam quaſi hominum exceſſerat metas, non verendo eum qui poſt Deum ab hominibus timebatur. <hi>Optat. adverſ. Parmen. lib. 3.</hi>
                  </note> above the Emperour there is none but God that created him. The Pope advancing himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Emperour, goeth beyond humane bounds, and carrieth himſelf, not as man,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:44571:65"/> but as God, in not reverencing him who of men is to be feared next after God. <hi>Aeneas Sylvius</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Pius II. de ortu &amp; Author. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perii, <hi>cap. 23.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Sit tandem finis li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium,</hi> Let there be an end of contention and one principal Head to determine all temporal matters, and the occaſion of perpetual debate be taken away; let men acknowledge themſelves ſubject to their Prince, and give reverence to him whom God hath made his Vicegerent on Earth. S. <hi>Bernard,</hi> though he lived but in a bad and corrupt Age, writing to a great Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop<note n="*" place="margin">Si omnis ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, etiam ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra; quis vos excepit ab uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitate? Qui tentat excipere, conatur decipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. <hi>S Bern. ad Hen. Senonenſ. Epiſt. 42.</hi>
                  </note>, <hi>If every Soul muſt be ſubject to the higher Power, then yours alſo among the reſt.</hi> The like may be ſaid of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> who hath given you an exemption from this general Injunction? He that endeavours to exempt you, doth but ſeek to deſtroy you. What ſhall we now ſay of thoſe who have blinded their underſtanding, and overturn'd their Morals? to think them Saints who have courage only to controul their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and fanſie it piety and devotion to laugh at what the Supreme Magiſtrate commands, is to exclude themſelves from the Kingdom of Heaven. It is a piece of new Divinity without colour of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or Religion, and was never heard of till Vice and Hypocriſie brought it into the World. And it is hard to ſay which
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:44571:65"/> is worſe, mens actions or opinions, that can turn the Dictates of the Holy Ghoſt to the temper of their own humor, and transform Religion into Fancy, Vertue into Speculation, Zeal into Contention, Truth into Policy, and Faith into Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that can ſee ſin in a harmleſs circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, a decency of habit, or uſage of a Ceremony, which are inſtances of our obedience, or our charity and unity, but can't diſcern thoſe greater lines of Duty, Subjection and Loyalty. And as the Scribes and Phariſees of old cry'd up eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where, <hi>The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord:</hi> ſo we have many ſuch now a-days, who are ſeemingly great Champions for the Church, and take great care of the Duties of the firſt Table, and yet can freely indulge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the violation of the ſecond, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving annoyances to the State by ſeditious Inſurrections, though the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion doth firmly oblige men to peace, obedience, and due ſubmiſſion unto Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Governours: there are many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that owne that Name, and yet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain Poſitions wholly inconſiſtent with the Precepts of that <hi>Religion,</hi> and the ſafety of Princes, and their Kingdoms, ſwallowing REBELLION<note n="*" place="margin">—There was a time, which is a precaution to poſterity, when men pretended a Call from God, to do the work of the Devil, <hi>viz.</hi> rebelling, and then murdering the beſt of Kings, erecting him a Scaffold for a Throne, and for a Diadem of Gold, gave him a Crown of Thorns, and inſtead of a glorious Prince, made him a glorious Martyr.</note> without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:44571:66"/> which opens the floud-gates of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, and lets in upon us a Chaos of Anarchy, Libertiniſm, and popular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, bringing a kind of preſent dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation on the World. They that are Authors or Abetters of Sedition, (ſaith S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) can neither avoid ſhame on Earth, nor eſcape eternal Damnation. Though God the great Judge do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times permit Rebels, in his Juſtice, to prevail againſt Kings for the contempt of the Law of the higheſt, and neglect of their own duty: the reward of Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion ſhall be no better than the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of Satan, who is the Inſtrument of the Lords wrath for the puniſhment of all diſobedience. The Kings Power is from God; and for any private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or any Club of Subjects to wreſt it out, is a double Uſurpation.</p>
               <p>Firſt, They invade Gods Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.19.</note> who ſaith, <hi>Vengeance is mine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, The Princes Prerogative, whoſe Office is to protect and puniſh, to defend the innocent, and correct the Spirit of Contumacy and Rebellion, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the oppreſſed, and ſupport the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous;
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:44571:66"/> rewards to Merit, as well as pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to Sin and Vice are diſpenſed: <hi>A terrour to evil doers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.14.</note> (ſaith the Text) <hi>and praiſe to them that do well.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore honour the King.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> As the goodneſs of Heaven ſhines in the preſervation of our Royal Soveraign from the Uſurpation of cruel Enemies at <hi>home;</hi> ſo likewiſe Divine Providence hath guarded him from Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Attempts of unreaſonable men <hi>abroad,</hi> and made the Plots and Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies of theſe (worſe than Heathens) of none effect, and deliver'd our King, and our Princes, our Nobles, and the Heads of our Tribes, the Governours of our Church, and Judges of our Land; nay, the whole Commons of this Realm, from a fearful deſtruction, that would have ſwallowed them up: For when the Ax is laid to the root of the Tree, to cut off Soveraignty, and deſtroy the Lord's Anointed, the reſt of the people, who are the Branches, muſt expect lop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping. The reſtleſs Emiſſaries of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> whether Prieſts, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, or Colledge of Cardinals, give dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proof of their inveterate malice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King, the Government, and <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion, thinking that new Maſſacres are the moſt effectual courſe
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:44571:67"/> to ſtop the cry of the old; and that the readieſt way to ſilence their Adverſaries, is to make them inſtances of the Truth of the Accuſation.</p>
               <p>If the great <hi>God</hi> of Heaven (who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frains the Spirits of men that delight in Blood) had not been gracious to our King and Kingdom, you had not this Day been Auditors, nor I Speaker of this Theme; but all of us miſerable Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the contrary: And the Pope's Triple Crown would have been ſet with many red Roſes of great Triumphs in a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, nothing leſs than utter extirpation of us, and Memorial from under Heaven. The Rivers of <hi>Rome</hi> may ſeem to run ſmooth, their Sea is Blood: the extract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Spirits of things work more forcibly than concrete Bodies, take heed of an Elixir, an Extraction of Malice ſublima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſpiritualized into a Religion. The cruel Maſſacres of Primitive Chriſtians<note n="*" place="margin">If we reflect on ancient times, and look back to the courſe of the World in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral; in the firſt Monarchy we find a fiery Furnace; in the ſecond, a Den of Lions; in the third, the madneſs and fury of <hi>Antiochus,</hi> when to believe in one God was to be put on the Rack, and to abhor Idolatry, involved the Votary in cruel Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: In the fourth Monarchy the ten Perſecutions more bloody and grievous than all that went before; for not to ſacrifice to Idols, and to offer Incenſe to Heathen Gods, was cauſe enough to be torn in pieces by wild Beaſts, and be expoſed to all manner of terrible Torments, when bloody Tumults affrighted Chriſt's Members, and chaſed them from their Devotions, when the Prieſt became the Sacrifice, and his Books in diſdain were made a Burnt-offering.</note> will teach us the price of our own hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, and the ſlaughter of our Forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may upbraid our unthankfulneſs with the benefits of our peace. 'Twere good that we their ſurviving Off-ſpring,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:44571:67"/> would learn to make uſe of their happy Martyrdom. In their crimſon ſteps we may trace the way to our Saviour's Croſs, and read in the living memory of their Torments the ſad Tragedy of his Sufferings. The World (at this day) is well mended with us; we know not the meaning of Rack or Faggot, of Sword and Gridiron, the Inſtruments of Romiſh Cruelty. Let three Kingdoms therefore bow themſelves as the heart of one man, and praiſe God for his mercy unto his Servants under the Protection of our gracious and religious King <hi>Charles.</hi> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven hath preſerved our Church from ruine and confuſion, from the ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and prevailings of Errours, Hereſies, and Schiſms, Superſtition and Idolatry, which ſtrive to oppreſs us, and to eclipſe the truth and purity of Doctrine, which is our Churche's Glory, and ſo much of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends the Eyes of <hi>Rome,</hi> and makes them clip, waſh, and new-coyn the Gold of the Sanctuary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> As Divine Providence and Goodneſs did this Day bring into the World our gracious Soveraign, and hath
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:44571:68"/> hitherto preſerv'd him from all Enemies, Domeſtick and Foreign: So the ſame ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial grace and favour of God, did this Day bring home and reſtore to us our King; a Prince of ſo much Clemency and Mercy, that he is inferiour to none that ſways a Scepter, or ſits upon a Throne. His Reſtauration was wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, without any Effuſion of Blood. The Voice of War is changed into Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Peace, the Clattering of Swords and Spears is turned into the ſweet Melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Harps, and the harſh Tones of Death into a Pſalm of Thankſgiving. O Lord, thou art become gracious unto thy Land, and haſt turn'd away the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptivity of <hi>Jacob:</hi> Praiſe therefore waits on thee in <hi>Zion,</hi> and unto thee ſhall the Vow be perform'd in <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> We celebrate the Memory of this thy Mercy, in reſtoring our King, and with him the free Profeſſion of true Religion and Worſhip. What doth God require now both from Prince and People, but the acknowledgment of his favour? He that will not glorifie God, as the Father of Mercies, in the rigour of Juſtice God may glorifie himſelf in his eternal ruine. If we prove not the Heralds of his Glory, Examples ſhall we be of his juſt indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. All taſting Mercy, all ſhould be
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:44571:68"/> thankful; and though all have not Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kincenſe, yet every one m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y have Praiſe. Let us praiſe God for his miraculous pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of our King and Kingdom, Church and People; and let it ſound ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oud (this day) as it may reach Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens gates, and meet with Hallelujahs, which the bright Morning-Stars in their Orbs pay to their Creator, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Angels Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy is ſinging of Hymns of Glory. And ſhall not the Militant Church ſay, We praiſe thee, O God; our Souls do mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the Lord? The Stork pays Tribute of her young, the Trees of their fruits, the Earth of her flowers, and ſhall we be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, without natural affection? <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, without God in the world? not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, return bleſſing and praiſe to the Divine Majeſty for his infinite Bleſſing unto us. We praiſe God in his Sanctuary, and in the Firmament of his Power, for his mighty Acts, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his excellent Greatneſs. Praiſe him with the Sound of the Trumpet, with Pſaltery and Harp, with ſtringed Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Organs; ſhew your ſelves joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful before the Lord the King. Let eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing that hath breath praiſe the Lord.</p>
               <p>Let us now direct our Prayers and
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:44571:69" rendition="simple:additions"/> Supplications to the Glorious and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Trinity, that all Bleſſings, Divine and Humane, Spiritual and Temporal like the precious Oyntment of <hi>Aaron</hi>'s may be pour'd out on the Head of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Royal Soveraign, length of days on hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> right hand, on his left Riches and Ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour; that his Reign may be glorious, and his Regal Vertues after this Life crowned with immortal Glory. And we with the reſidue of God's holy Church, may riſe to that incomprehenſible end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Felicity; where the Bleſſings of the Trinity in Unity, and Unity in Trinity, will gloriouſly ſhine upon our Souls for evermore. Which God of his infinite Mercy vouchſafe unto us, for the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of his Eternal Son, our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. To whom with the Father and Holy Ghoſt, three Perſons, one God, be aſcribed, as moſt due is, all Honour, Glory, Power, Praiſe, Might, Majeſty and Dominion, the reſidue of our lives, and for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 56. <hi>line.</hi> 13. <hi>for</hi> then <hi>read</hi> there, <hi>p.</hi> 62. <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>fo Reerſhaba</hi> r. <hi>Beerſheba, p.</hi> 74. <hi>l.</hi> 16. <hi>for</hi> fair this <hi>read</hi> this fair.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:44571:69"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
